<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE country-chap PUBLIC "-//IBFD//ELEMENTS COUNTRY-CHAP//EN" "http://dev-dtd.ibfd.org/dtd/regionalbook.dtd">
<country-chap anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01"
              infotype="Country_Survey"
              standardoutline="y"
              outlineyear="gtha__1_1.xml"
              collection="gtha_ar">
   <chaphead anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_chaphead">
      <pubdate pubdate="2020-11-09">9 November 2020</pubdate>
      <title>Corporate Taxation</title>
      <latestinfo anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_late">
         <title>Latest Information</title>
         <reviewdate reviewdate="2020-11-01">This chapter is based on information available up to 1 November 2020. Please find below the main changes made to this chapter up to that date:</reviewdate>
         <p>
            <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_ss_3">New proposal for tax reform.</xref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.7.">Extension of RECINE incentive to 2024.</xref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.8.2.">Deadline for filing ECF extended (COVID-19 pandemic measure).</xref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.8.2.">Phase-out of the SISCOSERV system.</xref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.5.1.">IPI zero rate extended (COVID-19 pandemic measure).</xref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.1.">Changes to ISS rules for certain services.</xref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.2.">Reduction of IOF rates on credit transaction further extended (COVID-19 pandemic measure).</xref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.4.">Proposal for contribution on digital services.</xref>
         </p>
      </latestinfo>
      <country cc="br">
         <countryname>Brazil</countryname>
      </country>
      <author anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_auth">
         <title>Authors</title>
         <name firstname="Fernando" lastname="Tonanni">Fernando Tonanni</name>
         <affiliation>
            <p spaceabove="0">Partner, Machado Meyer, São Paulo, Brazil</p>
         </affiliation>
         <name firstname="Alina" lastname="Miyake">Alina Miyake</name>
         <affiliation>
            <p spaceabove="0">Associate, Machado Meyer, São Paulo, Brazil</p>
         </affiliation>
      </author>
      <editor>
         <title>IBFD Tax Technical Editor</title>
         <name firstname="Vanessa" lastname="Arruda Ferreira" type="tte">Vanessa Arruda Ferreira</name>
      </editor>
   </chaphead>
   <chapbody>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_ss_3">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>The framework of the Brazilian tax system is set forth in the Brazilian Constitution, the Brazilian Tax Code and federal laws. The Constitution attributes taxing powers to federal, state (including the federal district) and municipal governments. As a result, the federal government, states and municipalities may legislate on related taxes within limits determined by the Constitution. Provisional Measures are also often issued by the President without the intervention of the legislature. Such provisional measures are valid for a 60 calendar-day period, which may be extended for another 60 days. Afterwards, the measures lose their effect unless passed by the Brazilian Congress and enacted as law.</p>
         <p>Corporate taxpayers are subject to corporate income tax (<emph type="i">Imposto de Renda da Pessoa Jurídica</emph>, IRPJ) and social contribution on net profits (<emph type="i">Contribuição Social sobre o Lucro Líquido</emph>, CSLL), hereinafter collectively referred to as corporate income taxes (CIT). Although the CSLL is, from a formal perspective, a social contribution, its taxable base and the general principles of its imposition are similar to the ones of the IRPJ. As a result, the CSLL is commonly viewed as a type of corporate income tax.</p>
         <p>In addition to IRPJ and CSLL, the federal government levies taxes on foreign trade (import and export taxes), a value added tax on industrial production (tax on manufactured products, <emph type="i">Imposto sobre Produtos Industrializados</emph>, IPI), a tax on ownership of rural land (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre a Propriedade Territorial Rural</emph>, ITR) and a tax on financial transactions (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre Operações Financeiras</emph>, IOF). The federal government also imposes social contributions on the gross income derived by resident companies (<emph type="i">Contribuição para o Programa de Integração Social</emph>, PIS, and <emph type="i">Contribuição para o Financiamento da Seguridade Social</emph>, COFINS contributions). There is also a federal contribution imposed on cross-border payments of royalties and certain technical, administrative and scientific assistance services (<emph type="i">Contribuição de Intervenção no Domínio Econômico</emph>, CIDE contribution). Taxes that may be imposed by states include a tax on the sale of goods, interstate and inter-municipal transportation, and on communication services (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre a Circulação de Mercadorias e Serviços de Transporte Intermunicipal, interestadual e comunicação</emph>, ICMS), which is a type of state value added tax, as well as a gift and inheritance tax (<emph type="i">Imposto de Transmissão Causa Mortis e Doação</emph>, ITCMD). Taxes that may be imposed by municipalities include a tax on services (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre Serviços de Qualquer Natureza</emph>, ISS), a tax on urban real estate (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre a Propriedade Predial e Territorial Urbana</emph>, IPTU) and a transfer tax on real estate (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre a Transmissão de Bens Imóveis</emph>, ITBI).</p>
         <p>A tax reform is currently under discussion at the National Congress under different parallel bills. Bill for Amendment of the Constitution 45/2019 (<emph type="i">Proposta de Emenda à Constituição </emph>45/2019) (Bill 45/2019) proposes a tax reform to simplify the Brazilian tax system through the unification of taxes and contributions charged on consumption. Under the proposal, the five taxes and contributions currently collected by the federal government, federal states and municipalities would be replaced by a single value added tax named “single tax on goods and services” (<emph type="i">Imposto Único sobre Bens e Serviços</emph>, IBS). Bill 45/2019 is currently under discussion at the National Congress.</p>
         <p>Bill for Amendment of the Constitution 110/2019 – Bill 110/2019 also proposes a tax reform to simplify the tax system through the unification of eight taxes and contributions, currently collected by the federal government, federal states and municipalities, into a state single value added tax also named IBS and a federal tax on specific goods and services named “selective tax” (<emph type="i">imposto seletivo</emph>). Bill 110/2019 is under discussion at the National Congress. In addition, Bill 3887/2020 (<emph type="i">Projeto de Lei</emph> 3887/2020) proposes to unify PIS and COFINS contributions into one contribution on goods and services (<emph type="i">Contribuição sobre Bens e Serviços</emph>, CBS).</p>
         <p>In addition, Complementary Bill (<emph type="i">Projeto de lei Complementar</emph>) was submitted to the National Congress on 19 August 2020 with a proposal to create a contribution on digital services (<emph type="i">Contribuição Social sobre Serviços Digitais</emph>, CSSD) to be levied on gross revenue derived by resident and non-resident companies from digital services targeting the Brazilian market. Both proposals are still under discussion at the National Congress.</p>
         <p>In addition, specific proposals to tax digital services provided by non-resident companies are also being discussed by the National Congress – see <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.3.">sections 9.6.3.</xref> and <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.4.">9.6.4.</xref>
         </p>
         <p>There is no ring fencing regime. In some tax treaties, the territory of Brazil is defined as “the continental and insular earth and its corresponding air space, as well as the territorial sea and its corresponding seabed and subsoil, within which, in accordance with international law and the Brazilian laws, the rights of Brazil may be exercised”. There are no tax autonomous areas or areas in Brazil where the Brazilian tax system does not apply.</p>
         <p>The federal tax administration agency in Brazil is the Brazilian Revenue Service (<emph type="i">Receita Federal do Brasil</emph>, RFB), which is in charge of the administration and collection of federal taxes and contributions. The finance departments of states and municipalities are in charge of the administration and collection of state and municipal taxes.</p>
         <p>The currency is the Brazilian real (BRL).</p>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1." label="1.">
         <taxtopics>
            <taxtopic tc="1_1" score="3">Corporate Taxation</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <taxtopics version="3.0">
            <taxtopic tc="1_1" score="3">Corporate Taxation</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <title>Corporate Income Tax</title>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.1." label="1.1.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Type of tax system</title>
            <p>Companies are subject to corporate income taxes (CIT) on a yearly or quarterly basis and generally on the so-called "actual profits" (<emph type="i">lucro real</emph>), which are computed in accordance with accounting rules and tax legislation (i.e. accounting profits adjusted for tax purposes) – other regimes for assessing profits subject to CIT may apply in certain cases (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.1.">1.3.1.</xref>). Generally, taxable profits include revenue earned as the product of capital or services, or a combination thereof, as well as all gains resulting from the disposal of a taxpayer's assets or rights.</p>
            <p>Economic double taxation is avoided via a dividend exemption system, under which dividends distributed to either resident or non-resident shareholders from after-tax profits are not subject to any further taxation (<emph type="i">see</emph> sections <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.2.">1.3.2.</xref> and <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.1.">6.3.1.</xref>).</p>
            <p>Brazil taxes income on a worldwide basis.</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.2." label="1.2.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1" score="3">Taxing Jurisdiction</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_1" score="3">Resident</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_2" score="3">Non-Resident</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_52_1" score="3">Hybrid(s) Entities / Instruments</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_52_2" score="3">Partnerships</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_52_3" score="3">Trusts / Estates</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_15_1_1_1" score="3">Fixed Place of Business</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_15_1_1_2" score="3">Fixed Base</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1" score="3">Taxing Jurisdiction</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_1" score="3">Resident</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_2" score="3">Non-Resident</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_52_1" score="3">Hybrid(s) Entities / Instruments</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_52_2" score="3">Partnerships</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_52_3" score="3">Trusts / Estates</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_51_1_6" score="3">Fixed Place of Business</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Taxable persons</title>
            <p>Corporate income taxes are levied on income derived by all companies established in or operating within Brazil. Resident companies are those incorporated under Brazilian law. Unincorporated business units, silent partnerships (<emph type="i">sociedade em conta de participação</emph>) and some types of investment clubs are also treated as corporate taxpayers. A consortium of companies, although registered with the federal tax authorities, is not subject to CIT in its capacity as a consortium. Instead, the companies participating in the consortium are liable for all taxes due on the result of the activities carried out in proportion to their participation in the consortium.</p>
            <p>Brazilian tax law does not provide for a concept of permanent establishment. However, it allows non-residents to operate in Brazil upon the filing of a request with the Ministry of Commerce, Industry and Development seeking authorization to carry out business activities locally through branches, which are subject to tax in Brazil under the rules applicable to resident companies. Private Ruling 351/2017 clarified that branches of foreign legal entities located in Brazil are treated as resident companies for tax purposes and, as a consequence, branches are also entitled to exemptions normally available to resident companies.</p>
            <p>Without making reference to the term permanent establishment, Brazilian tax law addresses situations under which a non-resident taxpayer may constitute a taxable presence in Brazil without being formally registered in the country (e.g. official representatives, commissionaires, local agencies, representative offices or business or professional units) – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2.1.">6.2.1.</xref> In such cases, non-residents are subject to tax in Brazil, under the rules applicable to resident companies.</p>
            <p>Non-profit companies are exempt from corporate income taxes, provided that certain conditions are fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Brazilian law does not recognize the concept of trusts or of hybrid entities, i.e. entities with legal personality that are not regarded as taxable units for tax purposes, such as transparent partnerships.</p>
            <p>As a general rule, funds in Brazil are tax-exempt entities (some exceptions apply, such as real estate funds and for-profit open private pension funds), while investors are taxed.</p>
            <p>This chapter is restricted to resident corporations (<emph type="i">sociedade anônima</emph>, S.A.) and limited liability companies (<emph type="i">sociedade por quotas de responsabilidade limitada</emph>, LTDA, referred to as simply <emph type="i">limitada</emph>). These entities will be collectively referred to as companies.</p>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.2.1." label="1.2.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1" score="3">Resident / Residence</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1" score="3">Residence</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Residence</title>
               <p>Under domestic law, a company is deemed to be resident in Brazil for tax purposes if it is incorporated under Brazilian law.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3." label="1.3.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21" score="3">Base</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21" score="3">Base</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Taxable income</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.1." label="1.3.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24" score="3">Income Streams</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_11" score="3">Income Characterization / Classification</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_1" score="3">National / Federal</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_11" score="3">Interest</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24" score="3">Income Streams</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_11" score="3">Income Characterization / Classification</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_1" score="3">National / Federal</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_11" score="3">Interest</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>General</title>
               <p>The main legislation on taxable income includes: Law 11,638 of 27 December 2007, Law 11,941 of 27 May 2009, Law 12,973/2014 of 13 May 2014, Normative Instruction 1,700/2017 of 16 March, Complementary Law 123 of 14 December 2006 and Complementary Law 155 of 27 October 2016. Companies resident in Brazil are subject to income tax on a worldwide basis.</p>
               <p>Income is broadly defined as all revenue earned as the product of capital or services, or a combination thereof, as well as all gains resulting from the disposal of a taxpayer’s assets or rights. Corporate income taxes are, therefore, imposed on income derived from industrial and commercial transactions, as well as on the rendering of services. Financial revenue, income from portfolio investments and gains from the disposal of other assets or rights are also included in taxable income.</p>
               <p>In view of non-standard CFC rules, resident companies in Brazil must include not only the foreign-source income that it derives (either directly or through a foreign permanent establishment), but also the profits earned by its foreign controlled or affiliated companies in proportion to the percentage of capital that the Brazilian parent company holds in the foreign subsidiary (for CFC rules, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.4.">7.4.</xref>). Dividends paid by resident companies out of after-tax profits are generally exempt from corporate income tax and, therefore, are neither included in the taxable base nor subject to withholding tax.</p>
               <p>As a general rule, income is taxable in the tax period in which it accrues, and the related expenses are deductible in the tax period in which they are incurred, regardless of when receipt and payment occur (accrual basis). In certain exceptional circumstances (as set out under the applicable laws), income and expenses may be determined on a cash basis.</p>
               <p>Taxable income is generally computed in accordance with accounting rules and tax legislation (i.e. accounting profits adjusted for tax purposes) – some exceptions apply (<emph type="i">see further</emph> below). Brazilian generally accepted accounting principles were adjusted in 2007 in order to become in line with the International Financial Reporting Standards. Law 12,973/2014 of 13 May 2014 dealt with the tax effects arising from the changes to the new accounting standards (previously, a transitory regime applied, in which legal entities could use old accounting rules for tax purposes). According to Law 12,973/2014, as of 2015 legal entities must observe the new accounting standards also for tax purposes (and no longer apply the transitory regime), unless regulated otherwise by the law. In view of this, Law 12,973/2014 brought relevant changes to the tax legislation in force in what concerns the assessment of CIT, PIS and COFINS, tax treatment of dividends, interest on net equity, the equity pick-up (<emph type="i">método de equivalência patrimonial</emph>) and tax amortization of goodwill, among other topics.</p>
               <p>Brazilian law basically recognizes four calculation regimes for corporate income taxes, namely (i) the actual profit regime, (ii) the presumed profit regime, (iii) the profit as determined by the tax authorities (determined profit) and (iv) the simplified regime for collection of taxes (SIMPLES). Other specific regimes are also available for some types of activities (such as the Special Tax Regime for Real Estate Development, among others).</p>
               <topic>
                  <title>Actual profit regime</title>
                  <p>Certain companies are obliged to calculate their corporate income tax liability under the actual profit regime, namely:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>companies having total gross income exceeding BRL 78 million in the previous year;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>financial institutions, insurance companies and other similar entities;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>companies deriving profits, income or capital gains from abroad (this does not include the export of goods or services);</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>companies which have been granted a tax exemption or reduction;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>companies which, in the course of the calendar year, have made monthly tax payments on an estimated basis;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>companies engaged in factoring activities; and</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>companies engaged in securitization of real estate, financial and agribusiness credits.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Under the actual profit regime, companies calculate their CIT liability annually or quarterly (at their discretion, based on an option exercised at the beginning of the year) on the accounting net profits for the taxable period, calculated on the basis of generally accepted accounting principles, adjusted by additions and exclusions provided by tax law.</p>
                  <p>With regard to net profit adjustments:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>as a rule, income is recorded on an accrual basis (with some exceptions, such as income from the sale of real estate units by real estate developers and income from long-term agreements for the provision of services or manufacturing of products);</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>only necessary and usual expenses and costs incurred by companies are deductible; and</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>profits of controlled or affiliated companies, in Brazil or abroad, must be recorded by applying the equity method.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>For applicable rates, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.1.">1.6.1.</xref>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the annual assessment system is adopted, companies must make tax payments every month on an estimated basis. In this case, companies calculate the actual amount of tax only on 31 December of each year and the amounts collected throughout the year are considered advance payments to the total CIT liability. Monthly tax payments are determined by applying percentages to monthly gross income, similar to the presumed profit regime (<emph type="i">see</emph> below), increased by capital gains and other gains arising from secondary activities. Alternatively, the taxpayer may calculate the monthly CIT payments based on interim balance sheets prepared by the company.</p>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>Presumed profit regime</title>
                  <p>Companies that are not obliged to adopt the actual profit regime may calculate their corporate income tax liability under the presumed profit regime. This is a simplified tax method under which the company calculates its taxable base by applying a percentage to its total gross income earned during the quarter (presumed profit).</p>
                  <p>Companies may choose to be taxed under the presumed profit regime provided their total gross income does not exceed BRL 78 million in the previous year or BRL 6.5 million times the number of months during which the company operated in the previous year (when less than 12 months). Law 12,973/2014 broadened the concept of gross income, which is defined in article 12 of Law Decree 1,598/77, in order to include, in addition to the amount derived from the sale of products and the rendering of services, other revenues derived from the main activity of the company.</p>
                  <p>The applicable percentages (for assessing the taxable base) range from 1.6% (for income from the sale of fuel and natural gas) to 32% (for income from the rendering of services, as general rule). No percentage applies to determine the taxable base of capital gains. With regard to the CSLL, the taxable base (presumed profit) is determined by applying a percentage of 12% or 32% (depending on the activity of the company) to the gross income earned for the quarter. For applicable rates, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.1.">1.6.1.</xref>
                  </p>
                  <p>Under this regime, the taxpayer may adopt the cash method for the recognition of revenue on transactions contracted for receipt in instalments.</p>
                  <p>If a company subject to the actual profit regime opts for the presumed regime, the losses incurred during the period in which the company was subject to the actual profit regime may not be carried forward to offset the profits calculated under the presumed profit regime.</p>
                  <p>The option for the presumed profit regime must be made when paying the first instalment of corporate income taxes in the year (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.8.3.">1.8.3.</xref>).</p>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>Simplified regime for collection of taxes (SIMPLES)</title>
                  <p>Micro enterprises, currently considered as those whose annual gross income does not exceed BRL 360,000 and small enterprises, currently considered as those whose annual gross income does not exceed BRL 3.6 million (as of 1 January 2018, the threshold is increased to BRL 4.8 million), may opt for a simplified regime for the joint collection of federal taxes, including corporate income taxes, the municipal tax on services and the state value added tax. In addition to the general BRL 3.6 million threshold, small enterprises and micro enterprises are allowed to have export revenues derived from the sale of goods and services not exceeding another BRL 3.6 million. Individual entrepreneurs treated as corporate taxpayers (<emph type="i">see</emph>
                     <extxref publish="n" target="gthb_br_s_1.4.">Individual Taxation section 1.4.</extxref>), referred to as MEI, may also adopt the simplified regime, provided that their annual gross revenue does not exceed BRL 60,000 (as of 1 January 2018, the threshold is increased to BRL 81,000).</p>
                  <p>Under this simplified regime, which is regulated under Resolution CGSN 140/2018, the taxable base for all taxes is determined by applying percentages specified by law to the gross income derived by the company. These percentages range from 4% to 22.90%, with some adjustments, depending on the level of gross income of the taxpayer and his business activities.</p>
                  <p>Some companies may not qualify for the SIMPLES regime, even if the revenue thresholds above are respected. Among others, the following companies do not qualify: (i) an entity incorporated as a corporation (<emph type="i">sociedade anônima</emph>, S.A.), (ii) a company having a non-resident shareholder and (iii) a company whose shares are held by other legal entities. From 1 January 2015, Complementary Law 147/2014 extended the list of business activities eligible for the SIMPLES regime to include any regulated service of an intellectual, technical, scientific, sportive, artistic or cultural nature, provided that certain conditions are met.</p>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>Determined profit regime</title>
                  <p>The determined profit regime is not an optional regime, but rather a regime adopted by tax authorities when the taxpayer does not comply with his CIT and ancillary obligations.</p>
                  <p>An income tax assessment based on profit as determined by the tax authorities is generally applicable where:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>the taxpayer fails to maintain commercial and tax records in accordance with applicable tax laws;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>the taxpayer’s bookkeeping evidences fraud, defects or errors which make it impossible to verify actual transactions undertaken or to determine the corporate income taxes due and payable by the taxpayer based on the actual profit; or</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>the taxpayer inappropriately opts to calculate and pay corporate income taxes under the presumed profit regime.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Under the determined profit regime, the taxable base is calculated by applying percentages specified by law to the gross income derived by the company. These percentages range from 1.92% to 45%, depending on the business activity of the taxpayer.</p>
                  <p>For applicable rates, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.1.">1.6.1.</xref>
                  </p>
               </topic>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.2." label="1.3.2.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Exempt income</title>
               <p>After-tax dividends distributed by resident entities are tax exempt. It means that neither withholding tax is levied nor dividends are taxed at the level of the beneficiary (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.1.">6.3.1.</xref>).</p>
               <p>Law 12,973/2014 also clarified that the dividends paid by equity-debt hybrid instruments (e.g. redeemable preferred shares) are tax exempt in the hands of the beneficiaries, even if they are registered as a liability for accounting purposes or as an expense in the profit and loss accounts.</p>
               <p>Other than that, there is no general list of exempt income. However, certain items of income may be exempt under special incentive regimes (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.7.">1.7.</xref>). For exemptions on capital gains, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.4.">1.4.</xref>
                  <emph type="i">See </emph>section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.">6.3.</xref> for exemptions regarding withholding income taxes on remittances.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.3." label="1.3.3.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11" score="3">Deductions</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11" score="3">Deductions</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Deductions</title>
               <p>Expenses paid or incurred (accrual basis) during the taxable period are deductible to the extent that they are necessary for the production of taxable income or for the maintenance of its source. The necessity of an expense is determined based on its relation to the activity of the company.</p>
               <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.3.1." label="1.3.3.1.">
                  <taxtopics>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_1" score="3">Deductible</taxtopic>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14" score="3">Losses</taxtopic>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_21" score="3">Goodwill</taxtopic>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2" score="3">Passive / Investment</taxtopic>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_11" score="3">Interest</taxtopic>
                  </taxtopics>
                  <taxtopics version="3.0">
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_1" score="3">Deductible</taxtopic>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14" score="3">Losses</taxtopic>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_21" score="3">Goodwill</taxtopic>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2" score="3">Passive / Investment Income</taxtopic>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_11" score="3">Interest</taxtopic>
                  </taxtopics>
                  <title>Deductible expenses</title>
                  <p>The most relevant legislation on deductible expenses includes: Law 12,973 of 13 May 2014, Law 11,196 of 21 November 2015 and Normative Instruction 1,397/ 201 3.</p>
                  <p>Special rules apply to certain categories of expenses, namely advertising expenses, amortization, bad debts, gifts and contributions, entertainment expenses goodwill, interest, directors’ remuneration and research expenses. Deductibility depends on specific conditions being fulfilled and is often limited.</p>
                  <p>In order to claim a deduction for cross-border payments of trademark and patent royalties and fees for technical, administrative or scientific assistance, the relevant licence agreement must be registered with the Brazilian Intellectual Property Agency (<emph type="i">Instituto Nacional da Propriedade Industrial</emph>, INPI) and the Brazilian Central Bank. The deduction of cross-border payments of patent royalties and know-how fees (for technical, administrative or scientific assistance) is limited to between 1% and 5% (depending on the business activity of the Brazilian payer) of the net income resulting from the sale of products or services by the payer. Trademark royalties are deductible up to 1% of the net income arising from the sale of related products or services by the Brazilian payer. The aggregate deductible patent and trademark royalties and technical, administrative and scientific assistance services is limited to 5% of the net income resulting from the sale of products and services.</p>
                  <p>Legal entities may deduct the interest which becomes due, even if not paid, calculated on a pro-rata basis in accordance with the accrual basis. As any other expense, deductibility of interest is available if the general deductibility conditions are met. Resident companies may also deduct interest payable or credited to a resident or non-resident shareholder or partner as a return on the capital invested by that shareholder or partner (interest on equity – <emph type="i">juros sobre o capital próprio</emph>), subject to certain limitations (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.3.2.">7.3.2.</xref>)</p>
                  <p>For limitations on interest deductibility, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.3.">7.3.</xref>
                  </p>
                  <p>Losses arising from exchange rate fluctuations are treated as financial expenses and may be deducted, provided that the general requirements for deductibility of expenses are satisfied. Gains and losses arising from foreign currency revaluation or devaluation are generally recognized on a cash basis, although taxpayers may elect to recognize them on an accrual basis.</p>
                  <p>Where certain conditions are satisfied, companies may deduct from gross profit (<emph type="i">lucro bruto</emph>) all the expenses they incur in the taxable period on research and development (R&amp;D) aimed at developing a new product or production process, or aimed at adding new value or characteristics to existing products.</p>
                  <p>Corporate taxpayers may also deduct from net profit (<emph type="i">lucro líquido</emph>) an additional 60% of the expenses incurred in R&amp;D activities. This deduction may be increased to a maximum of 80% of the expenses, depending on the number of employees hired by the company for research activities. Those deductions are available under the tax incentive for R&amp;D activities provided for by Law 11,196/2005.</p>
                  <p>Taxes and social contributions are generally deductible on an accrual basis. Interest payable because of late payment of taxes is also deductible. Punitive fines are not deductible.</p>
                  <p>Law 12,973/2014 provides that the payment in shares as compensation for the employee’s services is deductible only after the payment (when settled in cash or other asset) or after the transfer of the definitive ownership of the shares or options (when settled with equity instruments).</p>
                  <p>Payments made by a Brazilian entity to a legal entity that is either resident in a low-tax jurisdiction or is subject to a privileged tax regime are only deductible under the following conditions:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>the beneficial owner of the payment is identified;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>there is proof that the foreign legal entity has operational capacity;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>documentary proof of payment; and</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>documentary proof that the goods, services and rights were actually sold/rendered/granted to the Brazilian entity.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Deductions for interest on equity are not subject to the above conditions.</p>
               </section>
               <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.3.2." label="1.3.3.2.">
                  <taxtopics>
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_2" score="3">Non-Deductible</taxtopic>
                  </taxtopics>
                  <taxtopics version="3.0">
                     <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_2" score="3">Non-Deductible</taxtopic>
                  </taxtopics>
                  <title>Non-deductible expenses</title>
                  <p>Expenses that do not comply with the general tax principles or specific tax rules are not deductible, including values voluntarily paid by the company or that are unrelated to the economic activity performed by the company (such as entertainment expenses, among others), capital expenses and expenses related to exempt income. This limitation applies to depreciation, amortization, taxes, goodwill, repair or conservation fees and any other expenses related to movable or immovable property.</p>
                  <p>Under disguised profit distribution rules, transactions carried out by resident associated companies are subject to restrictions on deductibility through adjustments to net profits, with the aim of ensuring that the arm’s length principle is observed in such transactions.</p>
                  <p>Dividends are not deductible, including those paid under equity-debt hybrid instruments (e.g. on redeemable preferred shares), even if they are recorded as an expense in the profit and loss accounts.</p>
                  <p>Payments made to persons located in low-tax jurisdiction or benefiting from a privileged tax regime are not deductible, unless certain conditions are met – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.3.1.">1.3.3.1.</xref>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thin capitalization rules, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.3.">7.3.</xref>
                  </p>
               </section>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.4." label="1.3.4.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1" score="3">Amortization / Depreciation</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1_1" score="3">Plant and Machinery</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1_2" score="3">Immovable(s) Properties</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1_3" score="3">Intangible Properties</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1" score="3">Amortization / Depreciation</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1_1" score="3">Plant and Machinery</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1_2" score="3">Immovable(s) Properties</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1_3" score="3">Intangible Properties</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Depreciation and amortization</title>
               <p>Resident companies subject to corporate income taxes under the actual profit regime may claim deductions for the depreciation of assets and amortization of costs related to the acquisition of certain rights which use is limited in time according to Brazilian legislation (e.g. patents) and capitalized expenses from the commencement of their operations.</p>
               <p>Under the terms of section 57 of Law 4,506/1964, the deductions for depreciation are at the taxpayer’s discretion and according to some (non-binding) administrative tax rulings the depreciation may be postponed. In loss years, depreciation must be accounted for in the company’s net operating losses.</p>
               <p>Maximum annual percentage depreciation rates are specified for depreciation arising from the normal wear and tear of assets used in business activities, which are applicable under the straight-line method. Generally, depreciation of land is not permitted. Depreciation allowances are calculated based on the useful life of the asset when it is new, using the rates published by the Federal Revenue Service under Normative Instruction 1,700/2017. In the case of second-hand assets, depreciation is based on the greater of (i) half the useful life of the asset when it was new or (ii) the remaining useful life. There are specific rules governing accelerated depreciation of equipment and machinery.</p>
               <p>Maximum annual depreciation rates include the following:</p>
               <table anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_t_0">
                  <tgroup cols="2">
                     <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="6.69*" align="left"/>
                     <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1.00*" align="left"/>
                     <thead>
                        <row>
                           <entry align="left" colname="col1">
                              <p>Asset</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry align="right" colname="col2">
                              <p>Annual rate (%)</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                     </thead>
                     <tbody>
                        <row>
                           <entry align="left" colname="col1">
                              <p>Buildings</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry align="right" colname="col2">
                              <p>4</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry align="left" colname="col1">
                              <p>Office furniture and equipment</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry align="right" colname="col2">
                              <p>10</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry align="left" colname="col1">
                              <p>Aircraft</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry align="right" colname="col2">
                              <p>10</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry align="left" colname="col1">
                              <p>Automobiles</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry align="right" colname="col2">
                              <p>20</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                     </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
               </table>
               <p>If there is doubt concerning the depreciation rate applicable to a specific asset, the tax authorities or the taxpayer may rely on an appraisal by the National Institute of Technology (<emph type="i">Instituto Nacional de Tecnologia</emph>), or by another official entity engaged in technological and scientific research.</p>
               <p>No deduction is allowed for depreciation in excess of generally accepted rates, unless previously approved by the tax authorities. If an asset becomes worthless before the end of its depreciable life, the balance may be written off as an expense in the year in which the loss of value occurs.</p>
               <p>Normative Instruction 1,700/2017 established that if taxpayers do not deduct depreciation allowances of a fixed asset in a given period, they are neither allowed to deduct the depreciation in a different period in which the asset was used, nor to recover the non-deducted amounts by using rates greater than the maximum rates allowed.</p>
               <p>According to Brazilian law, from 2008, for accounting purposes, depreciation allowances are based on the rates applicable to the asset's useful life, which tend to be different from the rates in the tax legislation. From 2008 up to 2014, the tax legislation provides that taxpayers may opt between depreciated rates following the new accounting standards and the ones suggested by tax authorities. With respect to the calendar years starting as of 2015, Law 12,973/2014 establishes that the same tax treatment above should be applicable. Therefore, differences between the depreciation allowances for accounting and tax purposes should be controlled in the tax books of the taxpayers.</p>
               <p>Under certain conditions, companies may adopt accelerated depreciation and amortization rates depending on equipment and intangible rights. There is a general accelerated depreciation rule for assets on the number of hours used per day in the production process. There are also accelerated depreciation rules applicable to assets and intangible rights to be used for R&amp;D activities. Accelerated depreciation may be also available under certain incentive regimes (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.7.">1.7.</xref>).</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,794/2013, companies assessing taxable income under the actual profit method are entitled to use accelerated depreciation rates from 1 January 2013, provided that the qualifying assets were acquired between 16 September 2012 and 31 December 2012. The depreciation procedure and type of assets eligible for accelerated depreciation were established by Decree 7,854/2012.</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,973/2014, the following items shall not be computed, in the tax period in which they are incurred, for purposes of CIT assessment: (i) expenses related to the pre-operational or pre-industrial organization, including those incurred upon the initial phase of the operation, when the company used only part of its equipment or facilities, and (ii) expansion of the industrial activities. The above-referenced expenses may be amortized over a minimum period of 5 years from (a) the start of the operations or the full utilization of the facilities, in the hypothesis described in item (i) above or (b) the start of the new facilities' activities, in the hypothesis described in item (ii) above. Intangible assets, limited contractual rights and concessions related to the business activity of the corporate taxpayer (including infrastructure investments made in accordance with the concession agreement) may also be amortized over the period during which the right is exercised.</p>
               <p>Before Provisional Measure 627 (which was converted into Law 12,973/2014), goodwill was defined as the positive difference between the purchase price of an investment and the equity value of the controlled or affiliated company. According to tax laws prevailing until the enactment of Provisional Measure 627, goodwill had to be economically justified and be based on the following reasons:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>surplus of value of each of the invested company's assets;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>future profitability expected from the operations of the invested company; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>value of the ongoing concern, intangibles or other economically justifiable reasons.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>If the invested company is (i) merged into the investor, (ii) spun-off and the assets are merged into the investor or (iii) amalgamated with the investor, or vice versa, the company surviving the corporate restructuring may amortize the goodwill related to the future profitability of the invested company for CIT purposes, therefore generating deductible expenses (34% deduction). This deduction is allowed, provided that such goodwill is economically justified based on the future profitability of the invested company and duly evidenced as such (by means of a study or an appraisal report). Additionally, tax amortization must take place within a minimum term of 5 years as from the corporate restructuring. Conversely, if the goodwill is justified based on the surplus of assets and rights after the events mentioned above, it may be an object of depreciation or amortization according to the provisions of tax legislation.</p>
               <p>Law 12,973/2014 introduced a new concept of goodwill, aligned with the accounting concept currently in force in Brazil. Taxpayers have to recognize the balance resulting from the purchase price and the fair market value of the assets and liabilities of the company as goodwill. The minimum tax amortization term remains 5 years.</p>
               <p>Other relevant changes introduced by Law 12,973/2014 are:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the need for preparation of an independent appraisal report supporting the fair market value of the assets and liabilities of the company, which must be filed with the Brazilian Federal Revenue Service or the Register of Deeds and Documents; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>goodwill from transactions carried out by companies belonging to the same economic group is not subject to tax amortization.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The goodwill paid for the acquisition of an investment in a controlled or affiliated company may be amortized for tax purposes under certain conditions.</p>
               <p>Law 12,973/2014 also established that its ruling is applicable to acquisitions after 2014, for which corporate restructuring occurs after 2017.</p>
               <p>Law 8,981/1995 and Decree-Law 1,598/1977 established that the positive difference, if any, between the accounting value of fixed assets (considering depreciation, amortization or depletion) and the disposal value shall be considered for the purposes of CIT calculations.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.5." label="1.3.5.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_1" score="3">Deductible</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_2" score="3">Non-Deductible</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_1" score="3">Deductible</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_2" score="3">Non-Deductible</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Reserves and provisions</title>
               <p>Reserves and provisions are generally not deductible, with the exception of allocations to reserves for holiday payments and the 13th month bonus salary for employees, qualifying bad debts and technical provisions which are required under applicable laws for insurance companies, capitalization companies, and open private pension funds.</p>
               <p>A tax-deductible provision is allowed, under certain conditions, for duly substantiated and recorded bad debts that relate to the taxpayer’s business activity. No deduction is allowed for bad debts relating to loans made to a controlled, affiliated or related company.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.4." label="1.4.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_3" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_32" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_1" score="3">Shares</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_2" score="3">Immovable(s) Properties</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_12" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_3" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_32" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_1" score="3">Shares</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_2" score="3">Immovable(s) Properties</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_12" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Capital gains</title>
            <p>The main legislation concerning capital gains includes: Law 6,404 of 15 December 1976, Law 11,196 of 21 November 2005, Law 12,973 of 13 May 2014 and Law 13,043 of 13 November 2014.</p>
            <p>Capital gains arising from the sale of assets or rights recorded as the company’s non-current assets (former permanent assets), including equity investments and fixed assets, are included in the taxable base for purposes of the corporate income taxes. Taxable capital gains are defined as the positive difference between the disposal price of an asset or right and its book value. Taxable capital gains are recognized upon disposal by the company of the asset or right by means of, e.g. a sale, donation or contribution to capital. In the case of a contribution by one entity to the capital of another company through the transfer of an asset, the investor may transfer the relevant asset at its book value, i.e. without recognizing any taxable capital gain. Unrealized gains are not taxable.</p>
            <p>Gains arising from financial transactions and from the sale of portfolio investments are included in the taxable income of corporate taxpayers. These gains may be subject to a special withholding tax treatment (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.2.">1.6.2.</xref>).</p>
            <p>Corporate Law (Law 6,404/76) states that assets and liabilities related to long-term transactions must be assessed based on their present value.</p>
            <p>Law 12,973/2014 establishes that the present value adjustments must only be recognized for CIT purposes when, in general:</p>
            <list>
               <item label="(1)">
                  <p>the asset is sold;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="(2)">
                  <p>the goods are consumed as inputs in the production of other goods or in the rendering of services;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="(3)">
                  <p>the asset is realized by depreciation, amortization, exhaustion, disposal, or write-off;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="(4)">
                  <p>the expense is incurred (in case of acquisition of goods or service recorded as expense); or</p>
               </item>
               <item label="(5)">
                  <p>the cost is incurred (in case of acquisition of goods or service recorded as production cost).</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the cases of (1), (2) and (3) above, the amounts derived from the present value adjustment must be accounted for in subaccounts linked to the asset account. Law 12,973/2014 determines that the present value adjustment should not be considered in the assessment of CIT if: (i) the realized amount is not deductible for tax purposes (item 3 above); (ii) the expense is not deductible for tax purposes (item 4 above); and (iii) the amounts derived from the present value adjustment are not registered in subaccounts linked to the asset account (items 1, 2 and 3 above).</p>
            <p>Corporate law provides that assets and liabilities must be assessed based on their fair market value. In this respect, Law 12,973/2014 established that gains or losses derived from the fair market value adjustment are only considered for CIT purposes when the asset is realized, including by depreciation, amortization, exhaustion, disposal or write-off, and the liability is settled or written off. As a general rule, gains and losses derived from fair market value adjustments do not have any tax effect. If the taxpayer does not register the fair market value adjustments properly in subaccounts, gains are subject to taxation in Brazil and losses are not deductible.</p>
            <p>Law 12,973/2014 also covered the tax treatment of fair value adjustments when a corporate event takes place. Upon the implementation of a merger, amalgamation or spin-off, gains derived from the valuation based on the fair market value are not considered part of the cost of acquisition for the purposes of assessing the capital gains. Gains and losses registered in the subaccounts transferred to the successor must have the same tax treatment that would be applicable to the succeeded company.</p>
            <p>The capitalization of securities is deemed to be a sale according to Declaratory Act 7/2007, so that taxpayers who capitalize investment funds with their own securities are deemed to derive a capital gain (subject to income tax at the rate of 15%) on the difference between the market value and the acquisition cost of the security. For this purpose, investors must prove the acquisition cost of the securities; otherwise, the acquisition cost is deemed to be zero. According to Law 13,043/2014, with effect from 1 January 2015, the administrator of the investment fund is responsible for the calculation and collection of income tax levied on capital gains realized by investors who use their own securities to capitalize the investment fund.</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.5." label="1.5.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14" score="3">Losses</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14" score="3">Losses</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Losses</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.5.1." label="1.5.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14_1" score="3">Carry-forward</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14_1" score="3">Carry-Forward</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Ordinary losses</title>
               <p>Tax losses may be carried forward indefinitely, but such losses may be offset at a limited amount per year equal to 30% of the net profits (<emph type="i">lucro líquido</emph>) adjusted by additions and exclusions provided by tax law. The 30% limit does not apply when offsetting tax losses against capital gains derived by dormant legal entities or by legal entities being liquidated or under a bankruptcy regime, provided that the amount earned through the sale is used to pay debts of any nature due to the federal government.</p>
               <p>Non-operating (i.e. not connected with the main activity of the company) losses may be offset only against non-operating profits, except during the year in which they are generated. There is no carry-back of losses. Tax losses may not be offset if there is a change in the control of the company together with a change in the business activity of the loss-generating company. If the company generating the losses is merged into another entity, tax losses of the merged company must be written off.</p>
               <p>For foreign losses, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.2.">6.1.2.</xref>
               </p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.5.2." label="1.5.2.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14_1_2" score="3">Same Business / Activity</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14_1_2" score="3">Same Business / Activity</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Capital losses</title>
               <p>Capital losses may be set off against capital gains derived from the same type of transactions and are limited to the amount of such gains.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6." label="1.6.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_22" score="3">Rates</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_22" score="3">Rates</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Rates</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.1." label="1.6.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_32" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_1" score="3">National / Federal</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_3_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_32" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_1" score="3">National / Federal</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_3_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Income and capital gains</title>
               <p>Corporate income tax (IRPJ) is levied at the rate of 15%. A surtax of 10% applies on taxable income exceeding the annual amount of BRL 240,000. Social contribution on net profit (CSLL) is levied at the rate of 9% (for financial institutions, the applicable rate is 15% until 29 February 2020 and 20% as of 1 March 2020). The total effective tax rate is usually 34% (25% corporate income tax – including the 10% surtax – plus 9% for social contribution on net profits).</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.2." label="1.6.2.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1" score="3">Income Streams</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_1" score="3">Private</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_2" score="3">Public</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_1" score="3">Management</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_2" score="3">Technical</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_1" score="3">Shares</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_12" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1" score="3">Income Streams</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_1" score="3">Private</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_2" score="3">Public</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_1" score="3">Management</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_2" score="3">Technical</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_1" score="3">Shares</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_12" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Withholding taxes on domestic payments</title>
               <p>The main rules concerning withholding tax on domestic payments are found in Law 13,043 of 13 November 2014.</p>
               <p>Certain payments between resident entities are subject to withholding tax (as an advance payment of income tax), for example:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>payments for certain listed services or as a commission for agency, brokerage or other similar services, or for advertising and publicity services, at the rate of 1.5% (on an accrual basis);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>undocumented disbursements and any income or capital gains paid to an unidentified recipient, at the rate of 35%;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>payments of interest on net equity by companies (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.3.1.">1.3.3.1.</xref>) to shareholders, at the rate of 15%;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>fixed or variable yield income (including income from swap transactions, transactions involving gold as a financial instrument and interest paid on credit transactions, but excluding income arising from portfolio investments in the Brazilian Stock Exchange and day-trading transactions) received by a Brazilian company, at rates ranging from 15% to 22.5%, depending on the term of the investment;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>financial transactions carried out on the Brazilian Stock Exchange (except day-trading transactions), at the rate of 0.005%; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>day-trading transactions carried out on the Brazilian Stock Exchange, at the rate of 1%.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Earnings arising from investment funds and other financial investments are subject to special withholding tax rules, depending on the type of investment and fund. For example, income derived by an investor from investments in qualifying long or short-term investment funds is taxed periodically twice a year, on the last weekdays of May and November, at a 20% rate in case of a short-termed fund or 15% for long-term funds (the so-called <emph type="i">come-cotas</emph>). The tax is paid by means of liquidating an amount of the investor’s quotas sufficient to cover the tax liability.</p>
               <p>In general, the income tax withheld at source is treated as an advance payment of the corporate income tax due by the recipient at the end of the taxable period. An exception applies to payments to unidentified recipients, in which case the withholding tax is final taxation. The payer obliged to withhold income tax is jointly liable for the tax due, penalties and interest on late payments.</p>
               <p>For the withholding tax regime applicable on payments to non-resident companies, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.">6.3.</xref>
               </p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.7." label="1.7.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_2" score="3">Incentives</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1_1" score="3">Plant and Machinery</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_23_2" score="3">Investment Tax Credits</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_71_1_1" score="3">Trade</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_71_11" score="3">Ring Fence Regimes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_71_21" score="3">Special Types of Activities</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_2" score="3">Incentives</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_12_1_1" score="3">Plant and Machinery</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_23_2" score="3">Investment Tax Credits</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_71_1" score="3">Zones</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_71_11" score="3">Ring Fence Regimes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_71" score="3">Special Regimes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Incentives</title>
            <p>Unlike many other developing countries, Brazil has not adopted a policy of granting tax incentives to attract foreign investors. Nevertheless, there are some federal tax incentives aimed at encouraging investments in certain listed activities, as well as activities that are deemed to be essential for the economic development of less developed areas of the country. Key tax incentives include:</p>
            <list>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the tax incentive for projects of installation, modernization, expansion or diversification of industrial or agricultural enterprises in the north-east and Amazon regions (SUDAM and SUDENE), approved until 31 December 2023, which includes reduction of corporate income tax, accelerated depreciation, credits for the contribution based on gross income (<emph type="i">Contribuição Previdenciária sobre a Receita Bruta</emph>, CPRB) and exemption on taxes on imported goods;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the tax incentive for software development and information technology services (REPES), which includes a suspension of social contributions on gross income (which may be converted into an exemption under certain conditions). This incentive is not limited in time;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the tax incentive for the acquisition of capital goods by exporting companies (RECAP), which includes a suspension of social contributions on gross income (which may be converted into an exemption under certain conditions). This incentive is valid for 3 years from the date the taxpayer is allowed to apply it;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the tax incentive for research and development (R&amp;D) activities, which includes certain deductions and accelerated amortization and depreciation for corporate income tax purposes, reduction of the tax on manufactured products (IPI) and a reduced withholding tax rate (0%) for certain remittances;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for free zones and bonded warehouses, which include accelerated depreciation for the purpose of corporate income taxes and credits for social contributions on gross income. The applicability of the tax benefits in all free trade zone areas created until 11 August 2014 expires on 31 December 2050. The tax benefits granted within the free economic zone of Manaus expire in 2073;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for companies implementing approved infrastructure projects in the following sectors: transport, port, energy, basic sanitation and irrigation (REIDI). These incentives are granted for 5 years from the approval of the project;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for contributions to cultural and artistic projects;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for investments in infrastructure projects, digital TV and semiconductors (PADIS), valid until 2021;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for contributions to sports-related projects (from 2007 to 2022);</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for exporters (<emph type="i">Programa Preponderantemente Exportador</emph>, PEC);</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for research and development (R&amp;D) activities carried out by IT companies (Law 13,674/2018 – the so-called IT Law incentive (<emph type="i">incentivo Lei de Informática</emph>)), valid until 2029;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for the development of infrastructure related to the oil business in the north, northeast and central regions of Brazil (REPENEC);</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for economic use of goods in the exploration and exploitation of oil, natural gas and other fluid hydrocarbons (<emph type="i">Regime aduaneiro especial de utilização econômica destinado a bens a serem utilizados nas atividades de exploração, desenvolvimento e produção das jazidas de petróleo e de gás natural,</emph> REPETRO-SPED), valid until 31 December 2040;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for the industrialization of goods used for the exploration, production and exploitation of oil, natural gas and other fluid hydrocarbons (<emph type="i">Repetro-Industrialização</emph>), valid until 31 December 2040;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for permanent importation of goods for the exploration and exploitation of oil, natural gas and other fluid hydrocarbons, effective from 1 January 2018 and applicable to taxable events occurring until 2022;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>special tax regime for the National Defence Industry (<emph type="i">Regime Especial Tributário para a Indústria de Defesa</emph>, RETID) for companies conducting activities related to products considered to be of strategic interest for the national defence (introduced by Law 12,598/2012);</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>special tax regime for the Development of Cinematographic Exhibition Activities (<emph type="i">Regime Especial de Tributação para Desenvolvimento da Atividade de Exibição Cinematográfica</emph>, RECINE) to foster the construction of movie theatres in less developed regions as well as in popular neighbourhoods of big cities (introduced by Law 12,599/2012 and Law 13,594/2018), available until 31 December 2024;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>tax incentives for the coffee industry, such as the suspension of PIS and COFINS in certain cases and the granting of presumed credit for PIS and COFINS purposes (introduced by Law 12,599/2012);</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the “Greater Brazil” incentive package, introduced by Law 12,546/2011, where different tax benefits were granted, such as a reduction of IPI rates for the automotive industry, granting of presumed credits of PIS and COFINS for the biodiesel industry, deduction of certain expenses with technology and innovation for the purpose of corporate income taxes and replacement of the social security contribution by a contribution based on gross income for corporate taxpayers in certain business sectors; and</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>special tax refund regime for exporters of manufactured goods (REINTEGRA), originally introduced on a temporary basis by the "Greater Brazil" incentive package and reintroduced by Law 13,043/2014 on a permanent basis.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The World Trade Organization (WTO) issued, on 30 August 2017, panel reports on Brazil’s measures concerning automotive and information technology programmes (Dispute Settlements 472 and 497). The reports concluded that PADIS, the IT Law incentive, the Digital Inclusion Programme (no longer available), the Incentive Programme of Technological Innovation of the Production Line of Automotive Vehicles (<emph type="i">Programa de Incentivo à Inovação Tecnológica e Adensamento da Cadeia Produtiva de Veículos Automotores</emph>, INOVAR-AUTO) (no longer available) and the R&amp;D incentive for Digital TV Industry (<emph type="i">Programa de apoio ao desenvolvimento tecnológico da indústria de equipamentos para a TV digital</emph>, PATVD) (no longer available) are inconsistent with the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), the Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing Measures (SCM Agreement) and the Agreement on Trade-Related Investment Measures (TRIMs Agreement).</p>
            <p>Additionally, the panel concluded that the tax suspensions granted under the PEC and RECAP programs qualify as prohibited subsidies within the scope of the SCM Agreement.</p>
            <p>To the extent that aspects of the challenged programmes are inconsistent with WTO rules, the panel recommends that Brazil brings the challenged measures into conformity with its obligations under the covered agreements and that it withdraws the subsidies identified without delay. Brazil has filed a notice of appeal in both dispute settlements. On 13 December 2018, the WTO appeals body issued its report in both cases where it accepted Brazil’s argument in respect of PEC and RECAP and therefore reversed the panel’s decision on these incentives.</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.8." label="1.8.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="2_17" score="3">Tax Management / Procedure / Administration</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="2_17" score="3">Tax Management / Procedure / Administration</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Administration</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.8.1." label="1.8.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_21" score="3">Assessments</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_21" score="3">Assessments</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Taxable period</title>
               <p>In general, the taxable period is the calendar year. Taxpayers must report their results annually and file an annual corporate income tax return. However, companies being assessed under the actual profit regime may elect to adopt a quarterly taxable period. Under the presumed profit regime, the quarterly taxable period is mandatory.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.8.2." label="1.8.2.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_2" score="3">Filings / Returns</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_21" score="3">Assessments</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_71" score="3">Disclosure / Tax Shelter Rules</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_2" score="3">Filings / Returns</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_21" score="3">Assessments</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_71" score="3">Disclosure / Tax Shelter Rules</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Tax returns and assessment</title>
               <p>Brazil uses the self-assessment system under which all companies must file a tax return and declare their tax liability. Companies must electronically file the Digital Tax Bookkeeping (<emph type="i">Escrituração Contábil Digital</emph>, ECD) and the Fiscal Tax Bookkeeping (<emph type="i">Escrituração Contábil Fiscal</emph>, ECF) by the last working days of May and July (respectively) of the year following the taxable year. Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, however, the deadlines for filing the ECD and the ECF were postponed to 31 July 2020 and 30 September 2020, respectively.</p>
               <p>An Alert Program (<emph type="i">Programa Alerta</emph>) exists through which taxpayers can amend filing mistakes in the tax returns and calculations before a tax inspection takes place.</p>
               <p>Prior to establishing a tax inspection, tax authorities may notify taxpayers on the inconsistencies found upon the data crossing of tax authorities’ electronic systems. The existence of conflicts between the amount reported in the tax return and the amount in the tax authorities’ controls is notified to taxpayers together with the information on how to amend/review their declarations.</p>
               <p>Companies must also report their foreign trade transactions in specific systems controlled and monitored by tax authorities. Transactions involving the export and import of goods must be reported in the Foreign Trade Integrated System (<emph type="i">Sistema Integrado de Comércio Exterior</emph>, SISCOMEX). The SISCOMEX is a tool used by Brazilian tax authorities to inspect foreign trade transactions and the collection of taxes arising from those transactions. An electronic system existed (until 2020) for the registration of cross-border transactions involving services, intangibles and other situations that may impact the equity of Brazilian taxpayers (such as lease agreements and other types of transactions), which is called the Integrated System for the Foreign Trade of Services, Intangibles and other Transactions with an impact on equity (<emph type="i">Sistema Integrado de Comércio Exterior de Serviços, Intangíveis e Outras Operações que Produzam Variações no Patrimônio</emph>, SISCOSERV). The SISCOSERV was initially suspended from 1 July 2020 to 31 December 2020, and on 21 October 2020 it was officially abolished by the Ministry of Economy through Ordinance SECINT/RFB 22091/2020.</p>
               <p>In view of the COVID-19 pandemic, the tax authorities have been periodically suspending notifications and certain procedural mechanisms for enforcement of administrative collection of federal taxes. The measure also includes the suspension of exclusion of taxpayers from instalment regimes or the registry of non-compliance of requirements for purposes of tax registration.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.8.3." label="1.8.3.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_31" score="3">Payments</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_31_1" score="3">Final</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_31_2" score="3">Advance</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_61" score="3">Collection</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_31" score="3">Payments</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_31_1" score="3">Final</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_31_2" score="3">Advance</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_61" score="3">Collection</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Payment of tax</title>
               <p>Companies subject to corporate income taxes under the actual profit regime may choose to self-assess and pay income taxes under one of the following methods:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>determining the actual taxable profit quarterly, thus assessing and paying the corporate income taxes quarterly. In this case no annual corporate income tax is due, as corporate income tax on actual profits is paid quarterly. The deadline for payment of tax is the last business day of the month following the close of the quarterly taxable period; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>determining the actual taxable profit annually. In this case, monthly pre-payments must be collected and the taxable base, for this purpose, must be calculated (i) by applying a given percentage (which varies depending on the type of activity of the company) to the monthly gross income derived by the company, including capital gains and any other income except the income already subject to tax or (ii) based on the profits accrued on interim balance sheets prepared for this purpose. The tax must be paid monthly (by the last business day of the month following that in which the income is derived) and is treated as an advance payment. The negative difference between monthly advance payments and the total tax due at the end of the taxable year (assessed on actual profits) must be paid by the last business day of March of the following year or, if it is a positive difference, offset against the corporate income tax due in subsequent months (starting in January of the following year).</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Corporate taxpayers subject to the corporate income taxes under the presumed profit regime are required to assess and collect the corporate income taxes on a quarterly basis, i.e. considering the transactions performed within the quarter for purposes of defining the taxable revenue to be subject to the presumed percentages (which is the taxable base of the presumed profit regime). With regard to the corporate income taxes to be paid for each quarter, the company may credit the withholding income tax paid in connection with the income included in the taxable base. The corporate income taxes must be remitted by the last business day of the month following the quarter to which the CIT is related.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.8.4." label="1.8.4.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_41" score="3">Rulings</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_81_2" score="3">Enhanced Relationship</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_41" score="3">Rulings</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_81_2" score="3">Enhanced Relationship</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Rulings</title>
               <p>Taxpayers may present requests for formal consultation to the tax authorities regarding the interpretation of legal provisions and their application to the taxpayer's particular circumstances. The tax consultation request must contain a clear description of the facts and the subject matter. Decisions issued under this procedure are binding on the tax authorities only for the taxpayer requesting the decision, not for other taxpayers. In the case of effective consultations filed before the deadline to pay the tax, late payment penalties and interest do not apply on the subject matter of the consultation from the date of filing the request until the 30th day following the date of issuance of the formal decision. The request for consultation does not suspend the deadline for paying taxes that have been withheld before or after filing the consultation. The consultation does not suspend either the obligation to file the corresponding tax returns or to comply with other ancillary tax obligations.</p>
               <p>Decisions issued under this procedure may not be appealed. Nevertheless, if different decisions have been issued by tax authorities on the same subject matter but with inconsistent approaches, the tax authorities may, at the request of a taxpayer, issue a final statement regarding the matter under discussion, which will be binding on the taxpayers for which such decisions had been issued. This is aimed at unifying the position of the tax authorities.</p>
               <p>Decree 8,853/2016 amended the regulations on the consultation procedure, establishing that taxpayers may also question the classification of goods, services and intangibles based on the Brazilian service, intangibles and other transactions classification for international trade purposes. Decree 8,853/2016 also determined that the Brazilian Revenue Service has up to 360 days to decide on the consultation request.</p>
               <p>The exchange of information on tax rulings was regulated by Normative Instruction 1,689/2017 in accordance to Action 5 of the BEPS Action Plan on Base Erosion and Profit Shifting.</p>
               <p>Pursuant to this rule, information on any private rulings or divergence rulings may be exchanged with other countries if they deal with matters concerning preferential tax regimes or permanent establishments. In addition, taxpayers requesting rulings on those topics must disclose in their request forms the following information: (i) the identification of the direct or final controller of the legal entity requesting the ruling; (ii) the direct/final controller’s country of residence (if it is located abroad); and (iii) the country of residence of all parties with whom the taxpayer carries on transactions relating to the topic under consultation and of the country office and permanent establishment.</p>
               <p>The RFB committed to exchange information regarding those rulings to the tax administrations of the countries of domicile of the above-mentioned persons, with which Brazil has an agreement for the exchange of information.</p>
               <p>Normative Instruction 1,846/2018 (replacing Normative Instruction 1,669/2016) contains formal regulations to the mechanism for solving tax treaty controversies (Mutual Agreement Procedure, MAP). Accordingly, any Brazilian resident – individual or corporate – may require a formal procedure whenever it is understood that the application of the tax treaty is not in accordance with its wording and there is no administrative or judicial ruling on the matter.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_2." label="2.">
         <taxtopics>
            <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_1" score="3">Resident</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <taxtopics version="3.0">
            <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_1" score="3">Resident</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <title>Transactions between Resident Companies</title>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_2.1." label="2.1.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_41" score="3">Group Treatment</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_41" score="3">Group Treatment</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Group treatment</title>
            <p>There are no provisions for group taxation with regard to resident companies.</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_2.2." label="2.2.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2" score="3">Passive / Investment</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2" score="3">Passive / Investment Income</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Intercompany dividends</title>
            <p>Under Brazil’s dividend exemption system, dividends distributed by resident companies from after-tax profits are not subject to further taxation at the level of the recipient (i.e. are neither included in the taxable base nor subject to withholding tax).</p>
            <p>Foreign-source dividends are however included in the taxable base and subject to tax at the standard rates (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.1.">1.6.1.</xref>).</p>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_3." label="3.">
         <taxtopics>
            <taxtopic tc="1_1" score="3">Corporate Taxation</taxtopic>
            <taxtopic tc="1_5_12_1" score="3">Employer</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <taxtopics version="3.0">
            <taxtopic tc="1_1" score="3">Corporate Taxation</taxtopic>
            <taxtopic tc="1_10_12_1" score="3">Employer</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <title>Other Taxes on Income</title>
         <p>Under Brazilian tax law, there are two levies that, although formally introduced as social security contributions, are characterized as actual taxes on income, since they are generally imposed on the gross revenues of the corporate taxpayer (i.e. not on payroll). Those contributions are named contribution for the employees' profit participation programme (PIS) and contribution for the financing of social security (COFINS) and are generally regulated by Normative Instruction 1,911/2019.</p>
         <p>The taxable base of PIS and COFINS is the gross revenue. Law 12,973/2014 broadened the concept of gross revenue, which is defined in article 12 of Law Decree 1,598/77, in order to include, in addition to the amount derived from the sale of products and the rendering of services, other revenues derived from the main activity of the company.</p>
         <p>In a recent judgement, the Supreme Federal Court ruled that ICMS shall not be included in the taxable bases of PIS and COFINS. This lawsuit has binding effect on tax authorities and other taxpayers. The procedures for the exclusion of ICMS from the taxable base of PIS and COFINS are laid down in Private Ruling 13/2018.</p>
         <p>Companies adopting the actual profit regime for corporate income tax purposes are subject to PIS and COFINS contributions at an aggregate rate of 9.25%, with a deduction allowed for certain credits authorized by the applicable laws.</p>
         <p>Companies adopting the presumed profit regime for purposes of corporate income taxes (as well as other companies engaged in certain specific, listed business activities) are subject to PIS and COFINS contributions at an aggregate rate of 3.65%, but without deduction of credits (cumulative regime of PIS and COFINS contributions). Financial institutions are subject to PIS and COFINS contributions at an aggregate rate of 4.65% under the cumulative regime, with some special rules that allow the deduction of listed expenses from the taxable base (as per Normative Instruction 1,285/2012).</p>
         <p>Law 12,973/2014 had a major impact on companies making such contributions under the cumulative regime. In this case, companies with revenues not connected with the sale of goods or the rendering of services are subject to PIS and COFINS in respect of these revenues.</p>
         <p>Until 30 June 2015, financial income derived by companies subject to PIS and COFINS contributions under the non-cumulative regime was subject to those contributions at a 0% rate (except for the receipt of interest on net equity from domestic subsidiaries). As of 1 July 2015, the rates of PIS and COFINS have been increased by Decree 8,426/2015 from 0% to 0.65% and 4%, respectively. However, the 0% rate remains for financial income derived from foreign exchange fluctuation related to the following transactions: (i) export of goods and services; (ii) liabilities resulting from loans and financing agreements; and (iii) hedging transactions carried out on the stock exchange, futures exchange or over-the-counter market to protect the investor against price or rate variations, provided that the contract (a) is related to the operational activities developed by the company and (b) aims at protecting the company's rights and liabilities. Income derived by corporate taxpayers from the export of goods and services is not subject to PIS or COFINS.</p>
         <p>Law 13,043/2014, with effect from 1 January 2015, determines that income from the sale of shares is subject to PIS and COFINS only under the cumulative regime. The applicable COFINS rate on the sale of shares is 4% (previously, 3% under the cumulative regime and 7.6% under the non-cumulative regime).</p>
         <p>Law 12,973/2014 established that, for the calculation of the credits of PIS and COFINS:</p>
         <list>
            <item label="-">
               <p>the amounts derived from present value adjustments should be considered part of the acquisition cost of the assets;</p>
            </item>
            <item label="-">
               <p>gains and losses derived from the fair value adjustments of assets should not be considered for the calculation of such credits;</p>
            </item>
            <item label="-">
               <p>credits derived from payments made by the lessee under financial leasing agreements are not recognized for PIS and COFINS purposes; and</p>
            </item>
            <item label="-">
               <p>credits derived from amortization of intangible assets acquired in order to be used in the production of goods for sale or in the rendering of services are recognized for PIS and COFINS purposes.</p>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>In the case of listed products comprising basic consumer goods (<emph type="i">cesta básica</emph>), Law 12,839/2013 reduced the rate to zero for PIS/PASEP and COFINS levied on the import and commercialization of such listed goods. The basic consumer products consist of staple food and basic household items.</p>
         <p>The RFB clarified that royalty payments are not subject to PIS and COFINS contributions.</p>
         <p>In relation to some specific activities, the PIS and COFINS contributions are imposed based on specific rates and regimes, such as in connection with transactions with petroleum-based products, ethanol and cosmetics.</p>
         <p>According to Law 12,741/2012, as of 10 June 2013 companies are required to specify on invoices and receipts the taxes charged (percentages), which are included in the total amount of the product's sales price or the fee for the provision of services, including PIS and COFINS. Companies must therefore list the amount of municipal, state and federal taxes levied for each product described in the invoices and receipts sold. Such information could also be displayed on a panel in plain view within their establishments. Companies failing to comply with the requirements of Law 12,741/2012 are subject to administrative penalties.</p>
         <p>PIS and COFINS are also levied on certain import transactions. According to Law 13,137/2015, the standard rates of PIS-import and COFINS-import levied on the import of goods are 2.1% and 9.65%, respectively – the import of service is subject to the standard rates of 1.65% and 7.6%.</p>
         <p>Provisional Measure 774/2017, published in the DOU of 30 March 2017, revoked the additional 1% of the COFINS that was charged on the import of listed products. The measure was effective from 1 July 2017. However, Provisional Measure 794, published in the DOU of 9 August 2017, revoked Provisional Measure 774/2017. There is a controversy whether the additional 1% of COFINS is reinstated.</p>
         <p>The taxable base of the PIS and COFINS levied on the import of goods is the customs value of the goods. Previously, PIS-import and COFINS-import were calculated on the basis of a formula laid down by the federal tax authorities, which took into account the value of the goods and the taxes levied on their import. The taxable base of PIS-import and COFINS-import levied on the import of services remains, however, calculated on the basis of such a formula, published by the federal tax authorities (Normative Instruction 1,401/2013). </p>
         <p>Taxpayers under the non-cumulative regime may use PIS and COFINS credits with respect to those contributions paid on (i) the import of goods for resale and (ii) goods and services that serve as an input in the manufacture of goods for sale or the rendering of services, among others, to be offset against future payments of these contributions, among other specific hypothesis.</p>
         <p>For the new contribution based on gross income (<emph type="i">Contribuição Previdenciária sobre a Receita Bruta</emph>, CPRB) which is calculated on gross revenue and replaces the standard social security contribution on payroll for legal entities in certain cases, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_4.2.">4.2.</xref>
         </p>
         <p>There are no other taxes on income of corporate taxpayers. No state or municipal taxes are levied on income.</p>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_4." label="4.">
         <title>Taxes on Payroll</title>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_4.1." label="4.1.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_11" score="3">Payroll Taxes / Wage Taxes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_12_1" score="3">Employer</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_11" score="3">Payroll Taxes / Wage Taxes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_12_1" score="3">Employer</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Payroll tax</title>
            <p>The following payroll contributions apply:</p>
            <list>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the employer’s contribution to the unemployment guarantee fund (<emph type="i">Contribuição ao Fundo de Garantia por Tempo de Serviço</emph>, FGTS) is levied at the rate of 8% in order to ensure the severance payment upon termination of the employment contract;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the SESI/SESC contribution is levied at a rate of 1.5% for the purposes of cultural and educational facilities of workers;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the national service of industrial apprenticeship contribution (<emph type="i">Serviço Nacional de Aprendizagem Industrial</emph>, SENAI) and National service of commercial apprenticeship contribution (<emph type="i">Serviço Nacional de Aprendizagem Comercial</emph>, SENAC) are each levied at a rate of 1.0% (SENAI will be levied at a 1.2% rate, instead of 1% if the company has more than 500 employees); and</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>the SEBRAE contribution is levied as an additional contribution to SESI/SESC and SENAI/SENAC at the rate of 0.3%, for the purposes of promoting small enterprises.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the following reduced rates applied from 1 April 2020 to 30 June 2020:</p>
            <list>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>SESI/SESC: 0.75%; and</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>SENAC and SENAI: 0.5%.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_4.2." label="4.2.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_12" score="3">Social Security Contributions</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_12_1" score="3">Employer</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_12" score="3">Social Security Contributions</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_12_1" score="3">Employer</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Social security contributions</title>
            <p>The Brazilian social security system is financed by contributions from both employers and employees. Employers must pay social security contributions and charges based on their payroll and compensation paid to independent workers and directors, as well as other charges based on their gross income. In addition to paying their own contributions, employers must withhold and remit the contributions due from their employees and independent workers hired by them.</p>
            <p>Companies are subject to the following contributions:</p>
            <list>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>employer’s contribution to the Social Security (<emph type="i">Contribuição Patronal Previdenciária para a Seguridade Social</emph>) generally imposed at a rate of 20% on remuneration paid or credited to employees and independent workers. Financial institutions are subject to an additional contribution of 2.5%;</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>Workers’ Compensation Insurance (GIL RAT) contributions imposed at the rate of 1%, 2% or 3% on the payroll. The applicable rate varies depending on the level of accident risk on the company’s business activities. After the creation of the accident prevention factor (<emph type="i">fato previdenciário de prevenção</emph>, FAP), the SAT rate may be either reduced by up to 50% or doubled, based on the number and seriousness of labour accidents in the previous year; and</p>
               </item>
               <item label="-">
                  <p>contributions collected by the INSS and attributed to other official agencies at aggregate rates of up to 5.8%, depending on the company’s business activities.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Under Law 12,546/2011, the employer’s contribution to the Social Security, generally imposed at the rate of 20% on payroll, was initially replaced by a new contribution based on gross income (<emph type="i">Contribuição Previdenciária sobre a Receita Bruta</emph>, CPRB) for specific business sectors. Approximately 56 business sectors were entitled to the new contribution based on gross income, which was calculated at rates varying from 0% to 4.5% depending on the company’s activity and the products produced.</p>
            <p>Provisional Measure 774/2017, published in the DOU of 30 March 2017, reintroduced the standard employer’s contribution to the Social Security at 20% on payroll for listed business sectors, replacing the CPRB. Some business sectors (e.g. transport, communication and construction) are however allowed to continue collecting the CPRB, subject to rates varying from 1% to 4.5%. According to Normative Instruction 1,812/2018, this possibility is available until 31 December 2020.</p>
            <p>As the CPBR mechanism is based on gross income from the products and services specifically listed by the government and not the entire activity of the taxpayer, companies engaged in the manufacturing of some listed and non-listed products must adopt a mixed system for the calculation of the social security contribution.</p>
            <p>Companies are also subject to other types of social security contributions (PIS and COFINS) which are not levied on payroll but on gross revenues (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_3.">3.</xref>).</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_4.3." label="4.3.">
            <title>Other taxes</title>
            <p>There are no other taxes.</p>
            <p>For PIS and COFINS contributions, which are not levied on payroll but on gross revenue, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_3.">3.</xref>
            </p>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_5." label="5.">
         <taxtopics>
            <taxtopic tc="1_5_2" score="3">Capital / Property Taxes</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <taxtopics version="3.0">
            <taxtopic tc="1_10_2" score="3">Capital / Property Taxes</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <title>Taxes on Capital</title>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_5.1." label="5.1.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_2_1" score="3">Wealth / Worth Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_2_1" score="3">Wealth / Worth Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Net worth tax</title>
            <p>There is no net worth tax in Brazil.</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_5.2." label="5.2.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_2_4" score="3">Real Estate Holding Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_2_4" score="3">Real Estate Holding Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Real estate tax</title>
            <topic>
               <title>Federal tax imposed on ownership of rural land (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre a Propriedade Territorial Rural</emph>, ITR)</title>
               <p>The taxable event for ITR purposes is the ownership of property (<emph type="i">dominium utile</emph>) or possession of rural land located outside the urban zone of a municipality, at the beginning of every calendar year. Real estate includes the ground with its surface, accessories and natural adjoining areas, with trees and growing fruits, air and underground spaces. The tax rates range from 0.03% to 20%, depending on the size and productivity of the land. The taxable base is the market value of the land.</p>
            </topic>
            <topic>
               <title>Municipal tax on urban real estate (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre a Propriedade Predial e Territorial Urbana</emph>, IPTU)</title>
               <p>The taxable event is the ownership of property (<emph type="i">dominium utile</emph>) or possession of the property itself, located within the urban zone of the municipality at the beginning of the calendar year. Property itself means the ground with its surface, accessories and natural adjoining areas, with trees and growing fruits, air and underground spaces. IPTU tax rates are determined by municipal laws (e.g. 0.5%, 2%, 3.5%) and are not subject to any restrictions imposed by the Brazilian Constitution or the Brazilian Tax Code. The taxable base for IPTU purposes is the value established by the municipality, limited to the fair market value of the real estate.</p>
            </topic>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_5.3." label="5.3.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5" score="3">Other Taxes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_2" score="3">Capital / Property Taxes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_2_4" score="3">Real Estate Holding Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10" score="3">Other Taxes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_2" score="3">Capital / Property Taxes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_2_4" score="3">Real Estate Holding Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Other taxes</title>
            <p>The Special Contribution on the Increase in Property Value (<emph type="i">Contribuição de Melhoria</emph>) is levied on the increase in value of the taxpayer’s property as a result of a public work. It is calculated on a case-by-case basis, taking into consideration the total cost of the public work, allocated among the properties located in the area where the benefits arise. The special assessment may not be more than the value added to the taxpayer’s property (limited to the amount of the increase in the property value).</p>
            <p>A state tax is also levied on the ownership of land vehicles, such as automobiles (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre a Propriedade de Veículos Automotores,</emph> IPVA). This taxed is levied annually on the value of the vehicle (as registered by the federal state) at rates varying from 1% to 4% depending on the state.</p>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6." label="6.">
         <title>International Aspects</title>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1." label="6.1.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_1" score="3">Resident</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_1" score="3">Resident</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Resident companies</title>
            <p>For the concept of residence, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.2.1.">1.2.1.</xref>
            </p>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.1." label="6.1.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_2_2" score="3">Foreign</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_32" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_3_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_1" score="3">Controlled Foreign Corporations / Anti-Tax Havens [CFCs]</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_2_2" score="3">Foreign</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_32" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_3_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_1" score="3">Controlled Foreign Corporations / Anti-Tax Havens [CFCs]</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Foreign income and capital gains</title>
               <p>Brazil taxes resident companies on worldwide income and capital gains, including dividends and capital gains from the sale of stock of foreign corporations.</p>
               <p>Brazil taxes not only foreign-source income derived by resident companies (whether directly or through a branch), but also the income derived by foreign controlled or affiliated companies in proportion to the ownership percentage held by the Brazilian parent, as a consequence of the CFC rules (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.4.">7.4.</xref>).</p>
               <p>Foreign income is included in the taxable base and subject to tax at the general standard rates (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.1.">1.6.1.</xref>).</p>
               <p>No participation exemption applies.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.2." label="6.1.2.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14" score="3">Losses</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14_1" score="3">Carry-forward</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14_1_1" score="3">Same Shareholders / Control</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14" score="3">Losses</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14_1" score="3">Carry-Forward</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_14_1_1" score="3">Same Shareholders / Control</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Foreign losses</title>
               <p>Under Law 9,249/1995, as a general rule, foreign-source losses may not be offset against the taxable profit generated in Brazil. However, under Normative Instruction 213/2002, the results of permanent establishments abroad may be consolidated, provided that they are located in the same foreign country.</p>
               <p>Under Normative Instruction 213/2002, foreign controlled or affiliated subsidiaries’ losses may be set off against profits from the same foreign company. In this case, the 30% limitation for the offsetting of tax losses, applicable to profits derived within the domestic operations, does not apply.</p>
               <p>Law 12,973/2014 introduced a special treatment applicable until 2022 where positive and negative results (excluding foreign exchange results) by foreign entities controlled by Brazilian companies may be consolidated for purposes of application of the Brazilian CFC rules, provided that the foreign entities:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>are not located in countries without tax treaty or agreement with specific clause for the exchange of information with Brazil;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>are not (or are not directly or indirectly controlled by an entity) located in low-tax jurisdictions (<emph type="i">see </emph>section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.1.">7.1.</xref>);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>do not benefit (or are not directly or indirectly controlled by an entity that benefits) from privileged tax regimes (<emph type="i">see </emph>section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.1.">7.1.</xref>) or a tax regime with a nominal income tax rate less than 20% (the so-called “under-taxation” regime (<emph type="i">regime de subtributação</emph>)); and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>generate a percentage of at least 80% of active income.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>If the taxpayer does not opt for consolidation, the losses of the foreign controlled entity may be offset by future profits, provided that the losses are disclosed to the tax authorities according to the procedure and time limits established by the Brazilian Revenue Service (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.5.1.">1.5.1.</xref>). Accrued losses of directly or indirectly foreign controlled entities incurred prior to the new CFC rules (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.4.">7.4.</xref>) may be offset against the entities’ own profits, provided the losses are disclosed to the tax authorities according to the procedure and time limits established by the Brazilian Revenue Service.</p>
               <p>For CFC rules, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.4.">7.4.</xref>
               </p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.3." label="6.1.3.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_2_2" score="3">Foreign</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_32" score="3">Amnesty</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_71" score="3">Disclosure / Tax Shelter Rules</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_2_2" score="3">Foreign</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_32" score="3">Amnesty</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_71" score="3">Disclosure / Tax Shelter Rules</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Foreign capital</title>
               <p>There is no net worth tax. Real estate taxes are not imposed on property located abroad.</p>
               <p>However, under the programme for voluntary disclosure of non-declared assets abroad, income tax is due on the value of the disclosed assets – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.5.">6.1.5.</xref>
               </p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.4." label="6.1.4.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_32" score="3">Unilateral Double Tax Relief [DTR]</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_32_1_1" score="3">Ordinary</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_32_1_2" score="3">Indirect</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_32_1_11" score="3">Limitation</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_32" score="3">Unilateral Double Tax Relief [DTR]</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_32_1_1" score="3">Ordinary</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_32_1_2" score="3">Indirect</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_32_1_11" score="3">Limitation</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Double taxation relief</title>
               <p>The main legislation related to double taxation relief includes Law 12,202 of January 2010, Law 12,973 of 13 May 2014 and Normative Instructions 213/2002 and 1,520/2014.</p>
               <p>Unilateral relief is granted to corporate taxpayers by means of an ordinary foreign tax credit. Relief granted under tax treaties is applicable regardless of whether the relief is foreseen in domestic law (e.g. Divergence Ruling 8/2014).</p>
               <p>Taxes paid abroad on income directly derived by the Brazilian resident company may be claimed as a credit against the domestic tax liability. This foreign tax credit is limited to the amount of domestic tax that is imposed on the foreign-source income. For these purposes, the Brazilian tax liability includes both IRPJ and CSLL – <emph type="i">see</emph> the <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_ss_3">Introduction</xref>.</p>
               <p>Brazilian tax authorities take the position that resident entities opting for the presumed profit regime of taxation (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.1.">1.3.1.</xref>) and directly providing services abroad are not allowed to credit taxes paid abroad against taxes paid in Brazil (Divergence Ruling 8/2014). However, this prohibition does not apply if the service is provided in countries with which Brazil has signed a tax treaty where the elimination of international double taxation is agreed through the use of the credit method.</p>
               <p>An ordinary foreign tax credit is available for the tax on profit distributions by foreign subsidiaries and the underlying tax paid by the distributing subsidiary in the jurisdiction where the foreign entity is located.</p>
               <p>Until the enactment of Law 12,973/2014, the foreign tax credit was calculated separately for each company, with no consolidation allowed for different subsidiaries (i.e. a per-company limitation). After Law 12,973/2014, consolidation was permitted at the level of a foreign subsidiary of a Brazilian parent with respect to lower-tier subsidiaries.</p>
               <p>Until 2022, and provided certain conditions are met, controlling entities in Brazil may benefit from a credit in the amount of 9% of the positive result related to investments in foreign entities which are engaged in certain activities (e.g. production of food or beverage, construction, mineral extraction).</p>
               <p>Normative Instructions 213/2002, 1,520/2014 (as amended) and Private Ruling 185/2018 set forth the proceedings, clarifications and documents necessary for the offsetting of income taxes paid abroad by Brazilian corporate taxpayers.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.5." label="6.1.5.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_32" score="3">Amnesty</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_33" score="3">Interest &amp; Penalties</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_34" score="3">Offences &amp; Punishment</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_71" score="3">Disclosure / Tax Shelter Rules</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_32" score="3">Amnesty</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_33" score="3">Interest &amp; Penalties</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_34" score="3">Offences &amp; Punishment</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_71" score="3">Disclosure / Tax Shelter Rules</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Voluntary disclosure of non-declared assets</title>
               <p>Law 13,254/2016 introduced a special regime for the voluntary disclosure and regularization of non-declared (or incorrectly declared) funds, goods and rights of lawful origin which had been remitted or kept abroad or repatriated by resident individuals or companies (<emph type="i">Regime Especial de Regularização Cambial e Tributária</emph>, RERCT), which was open for applicants until 31 October 2016. The regime was however reopened in 2017 through the enactment of Law 13,428/2017, published on 31 March 2017.</p>
               <p>The regime in force in 2017 applies to persons who were residents of Brazil on 30 June 2016 and who held assets for a period of time prior to that date. Non-resident persons may also benefit from the regime, provided that they were residents of Brazil on 30 June 2016. Persons judicially condemned for listed criminal acts and public officials (as well as their spouses and relatives up to the second degree) are not allowed to benefit from the regime. Assets eligible for the regime included bank accounts, shares, intangibles, real estate, cars, vessels and aeroplanes. The regularization of the undeclared assets through the regime triggered the payment of:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>income tax at a rate of 15% on the total value of the assets; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>a fine equivalent to 135% of the income tax due (bank accounts containing less than BRL 10,000 are exempt from the fine).</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The voluntary disclosure of referred assets results in the granting of amnesty in respect of listed crimes related to the non-declaration of the assets. The deadline for applying for the regime was 31 July 2017.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2." label="6.2.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_2" score="3">Non-Resident</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_1_2" score="3">Non-Resident</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Non-resident companies</title>
            <p>The law does not provide for the concept of non-resident. In principle, all persons and entities that do not fall within the concept of resident (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.2.1.">1.2.1.</xref>) are characterized as non-residents. For the concept of permanent establishment, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2.1.">6.2.1.</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Non-residents are subject to income tax in Brazil if they derive income arising in Brazil which is from Brazilian residents, if they derive capital gains from the disposal of Brazilian-situs assets or rights, or engage in activities in Brazil through branches, official representatives, commissionaires, local agencies, representative offices or business or professional units (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2.1.">6.2.1.</xref>).</p>
            <p>Non-residents without a presence in Brazil are subject to a final withholding tax (<emph type="i">see</emph> sections <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2.1.">6.2.1.</xref> and <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.">6.3.</xref>). The CSLL does not apply in such cases. Branches, local agencies, representative offices or business or professional units in Brazil are taxed as resident companies.</p>
            <p>Services provided by non-residents to residents are also subject to ISS – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.1.">9.6.1.</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Certain cross-border transactions are also subject to PIS, COFINS (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_3.">3.</xref>) and/or CIDE (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.3.">9.6.3.</xref>), but the taxpayer in such cases is the Brazilian resident person (and not the non-resident).</p>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2.1." label="6.2.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_2_2" score="3">Foreign</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_32" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_11" score="3">Interest</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_3_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_1_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_1" score="3">Private</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_2" score="3">Public</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_3" score="3">Bank</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_3_1" score="3">Copyrights</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_3_2" score="3">Patents</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_3_3" score="3">Trademarks</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_2" score="3">Technical</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_1" score="3">Shares</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_12" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_15" score="3">Permanent Establishments [PE]</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_1_2_2" score="3">Foreign</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_22_32" score="3">Capital Gains</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_1" score="3">Active / Business</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_2_11" score="3">Interest</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_24_3_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_1_2" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_1" score="3">Private</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_2" score="3">Public</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2_3" score="3">Bank</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_3_1" score="3">Copyrights</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_3_2" score="3">Patents</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_3_3" score="3">Trademarks</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_2" score="3">Technical</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_1" score="3">Shares</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_5_12" score="3">Portfolio</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_51" score="3">Permanent Establishments [PE]</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Taxes on income and capital gains</title>
               <p>The main legislation concerning taxes on income and capital gains derived by non-residents includes: Law 13,097 of 19 January 2015, Law 13,259 of 16 March 2016 and Normative Instruction 1455 of 7 March 2014 as amended by Normative Instructions 1662 of 30 September 2016, 1664 of 11 October 2016 and 1732 of 25 August 2017.</p>
               <p>Brazilian tax law does not provide for a concept of permanent establishment. However, it allows non-residents to operate in Brazil upon the filing of a request with the Ministry of Commerce, Industry and Development seeking an authorization to carry out business activities locally through branches, which are subject to tax in Brazil under the rules applicable to resident companies.</p>
               <p>Without making reference to the term “permanent establishment”, Brazilian tax law addresses situations under which a non-resident taxpayer may have a taxable presence in Brazil without being formally registered in the country. These rules are not expressly related to determining whether there is a permanent establishment in Brazil, although the tax authorities could, in principle, rely on them to assess corporate income taxes on local “taxable units” of non-residents. One situation refers to non-residents that are subject to corporate income taxes on profits derived in Brazil from the sale of imported goods through official representatives (<emph type="i">mandatários</emph>), commissionaires (<emph type="i">comissários</emph>), or direct sale through local agents or representatives (a type of agency permanent establishment). Another situation refers to the concept of a business or professional unit, where a person conducts business activities without being formally registered with the competent authorities to do so (unincorporated business unit).</p>
               <p>Although there is no definition of permanent establishment in the law, when regulating the country-by-country reporting, Normative Instruction 1,681/2016 referred to a permanent establishment as a fixed business installation through which an entity exercises, totally or partly, its business activity in a different jurisdiction. The definition follows with an exemplificative list including “a place of management, a branch, an office, a factory, a workshop, a mine or any place of extraction of minerals and a construction site only when it exceeds the period of 12 months”. While normative instructions are technically administrative acts that are hierarchically below the law, they may serve as a basis for the tax authorities to challenge operations that are not being taxed in Brazil.</p>
               <p>A non-resident without taxable presence in Brazil in the forms described above may be subject to a final withholding tax depending on the type of income derived. Where no special rate is provided, a general final withholding tax rate of 15% applies. Generally, income paid to beneficiaries located in low-tax jurisdictions (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.1.">7.1.</xref>) is subject to final withholding tax at the rate of 25%.</p>
               <p>Business income derived by non-residents with a presence in Brazil (e.g. branches, official representatives, etc.) is taxed according to the rules applicable to resident companies. Non-residents without a presence in Brazil deriving fees from the provision of services are subject to withholding tax at a 25% rate (a rate of 15% applies for technical services) – for reductions on the rate, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.4.">6.3.4.</xref>
               </p>
               <p>Currently, taxes on capital gains derived by non-residents are generally withheld at source by the Brazilian payer, unless specific rules apply. Capital gains realized outside of Brazil in transactions involving assets or rights located in Brazil are subject to Brazilian income tax even if the transaction involves only non-residents. In this case, the registered representative of the non-resident purchaser in Brazil is legally liable for the collection of the income tax on capital gains due by the non-resident.</p>
               <p>With effect from 1 January 2017, Law 13,259/2016, further regulated by Normative Instruction 1,732/2017, established progressive final rates ranging from 15% to 22.5% applicable to capital gains derived from the disposition of assets by resident individuals (and consequently to non-resident companies, as the tax treatment applicable to non-resident persons in such scenario is the same as the one applicable to individuals), as follows (previously, a general rate of 15% applied):</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>15% on the portion of the gains not exceeding BRL 5,000,000;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>17.5% on the portion of the gains between BRL 5,000,001 and BRL 10,000,000;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>20% on the portion of the gains between BRL 10,000,001 and BRL 30,000,000; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>22.5% on the portion of the gains exceeding BRL 30,000,000.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>If the beneficiary is resident in a low-tax jurisdiction, the applicable rate is 25%. In the calculation of capital gain, the acquisition cost of the assets in Brazil must be proven. If non-residents are unable to prove the cost, it is deemed to be zero, as provided by Normative Instruction 1,662/2016.</p>
               <p>Gains derived by non-residents as a result of the sale of shares or other securities issued by Brazilian listed companies on the Brazilian stock exchange or on the organized over-the-counter (OTC) market, registered under specific rules issued by the Central Bank of Brazil, are exempt from withholding tax. An exemption also applies to investments made in local private equity funds, under specified conditions and rules issued by the Central Bank of Brazil.</p>
               <p>According to Law 13,097/2015, income and capital gains derived by non-resident investors from Real Estate Secured Bills (“LIG”), which is an instrument for long-term real estate financing, are exempt from income tax (except when resident in low-tax jurisdictions, in which case a 15% withholding tax rate applies).</p>
               <p>Law 12,973/2014 stated that the income (including capital gains) earned by non-residents (not located in low-tax jurisdictions) and arising from investment funds are exempted from income tax provided that:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the investment fund has only foreign investors as shareholders; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the investment fund’s regulation determines that the investment fund must have its resources invested in only demand deposits or in assets exempt from income tax or taxed at a zero rate.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Law 12,973/2014 also provides that the capital gain realized on the sale or redemption of quotas of private equity investment funds is subject to income tax at a zero rate, provided that certain conditions are met.</p>
               <p>Income from immovable property is subject to a final withholding tax – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.4.">6.3.4.</xref>
               </p>
               <p>Dividends are exempt – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.1.">6.3.1.</xref>
               </p>
               <p>Interest is subject to a final withholding tax – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.2.">6.3.2.</xref>
               </p>
               <p>Royalties are subject to a final withholding tax – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.3.">6.3.3.</xref>
               </p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2.2." label="6.2.2.">
               <title>Taxes on capital</title>
               <p>There is no net worth tax. Non-residents owning immovable property in Brazil are subject to real estate tax (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_5.2.">5.2.</xref>).</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2.3." label="6.2.3.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17" score="3">Tax Management / Procedure / Administration</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_2" score="3">Filings / Returns</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_31_1" score="3">Final</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17" score="3">Tax Management / Procedure / Administration</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_2" score="3">Filings / Returns</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="2_17_31_1" score="3">Final</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Administration</title>
               <p>Non-residents without taxable presence in Brazil are not required to file tax returns. Income is normally charged through a withholding tax system.</p>
               <p>A non-resident with a branch formally registered in Brazil must self-assess its own income tax liability under the rules applicable to resident companies.</p>
               <p>Non-residents owning assets and rights in Brazil (e.g. real estate, vehicles, share participations, bank accounts and investments in the Brazilian financial and capital markets) must register as taxpayers with the Brazilian federal tax authorities. They must appoint a local representative in Brazil and notify the federal tax authorities of the appointment. No tax return needs to be filed.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3." label="6.3.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_1" score="3">Income Streams</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_1" score="3">Income Streams</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Withholding taxes on payments to non-resident companies</title>
            <p>The main legislation concerning withholding tax on payments to non-residents includes: Law 12,249 of 11 June 2010, Law 12,431 of 24 June 2011, Normative Instruction 1,214/2011, Law 12,973 of 13 May 2014, Law 13,313 of 14 July 2016 and Normative Instruction 1,645/2016.</p>
            <p>Brazilian-source income derived by non-residents without a branch in Brazil is generally subject to a final withholding tax levied on the gross amount at rates varying depending on the type of income (<emph type="i">see</emph> sections <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.1.">6.3.1.</xref> to 6.3.4.). For reduced rates under income tax treaties, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.5.">6.3.5.</xref>
            </p>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.1." label="6.3.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_1" score="3">Dividends</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_1" score="3">Dividends</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_15" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Dividends</title>
               <p>Dividends paid by resident companies out of after-tax profits to non-resident shareholders are exempt from income tax.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.2." label="6.3.2.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2" score="3">Interest</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_2" score="3">Interest</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Interest</title>
               <p>As a general rule, interest, commissions and other financial expenses incurred on cross-border loans and paid to non-residents are subject to a final 15% withholding tax on the gross amount (for interest on net equity, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.6.2.">1.6.2.</xref>). A 25% rate generally applies to beneficiaries located in low-tax jurisdictions. There are some exemptions and zero-percent withholding tax rates established by domestic law, which are mainly related to export loans granted by export credit agencies, export financing, and loans granted by the International Finance Corporation or by governmental agencies and destined for the acquisition of equipment.</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,431/2011, under certain conditions the withholding income tax rate is reduced to zero for income derived by non-resident persons (except residents in countries that do not tax income or tax it at a maximum rate of 20%) from:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>bonds and securities acquired from 1 January 2011 and publicly traded by Brazilian companies classified as non-financial institutions; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>investment funds provided that at least 85% of the fund’s portfolio consists of debentures issued by companies specifically incorporated to implement infrastructure projects (income tax exemption).</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Law 12,973/2014 states that the income earned by non-residents (not located in low-tax jurisdictions) and arising from investment funds is exempted from income tax provided that:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the investment fund has only foreign investors as shareholders; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the investment fund’s regulation determines that the investment fund must have its resources invested only in demand deposits or in assets subject to income tax exemption or taxed at a zero rate.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.3." label="6.3.3.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_3" score="3">Royalties</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_3" score="3">Royalties</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Royalties</title>
               <p>A final withholding income tax on royalty payments to non-residents applies at the rate of 15%. A 25% rate applies to royalty payments made to beneficiaries located in low-tax jurisdictions.</p>
               <p>Pursuant to Divergence Ruling 18/2017, outbound payments made by importers for rights over the sale or distribution of software to final consumers in Brazil qualify as payment of royalties and are subject to withholding tax at a rate of 15%.</p>
               <p>Royalties paid by resident companies to non-residents as consideration for the transfer of technology, trademarks and patents, or for the supply of technical, administrative or scientific assistance, are also subject to the contribution for intervention in the economic domain (CIDE) – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.3.">9.6.3.</xref> This contribution is not withheld at source; rather, it is imposed directly on the Brazilian payer. The CIDE contribution is not imposed on cross-border payments for software licences, except for payments involving acquisition of software rights (transfer of technology)</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,741/2012, as of 10 June 2013 companies are required to specify on invoices and receipts the taxes charged (percentages) which are part of the total product sales price or the fee for the provision of services, including CIDE. Companies must list the municipal, state and federal taxes levied for each product described in the invoices and receipts. Such information could also be displayed on a panel in plain view within their establishments. Companies failing to comply with the requirements of Law 12,741/2012 are subject to administrative penalties.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.4." label="6.3.4.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_1" score="3">Management</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_2" score="3">Technical</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_6_2" score="3">Immovable(s) Properties</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_1" score="3">Management</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_4_2" score="3">Technical</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_3_1_6_2" score="3">Immovable(s) Properties</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Other</title>
               <p>Income from immovable property paid to non-residents is subject to a final 15% withholding tax.</p>
               <p>Payment for services in general is subject to a final withholding tax at the rate of 25% on the gross amount (a 15% rate applies to fees for technical service and technical assistance). </p>
               <p>An exemption applies to outbound payments made to non-resident persons for (Normative Instruction 1,645/2016):</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>educational, scientific or cultural purposes, including tuition fees, congress or seminar fees and proficiency exam fees; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>covering medical and hospital expenses related to medical treatment abroad (including treatment of dependants).</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>A reduced withholding tax rate of 6% applied until 31 December 2019 to payments made to non-resident individuals or legal entities to cover personal expenses incurred abroad by resident individuals relating to tourism, business, service or training trips, as well as official missions (Law 13,315/2016 and Normative Instruction 1,645/2016). The reduced rate applied only to monthly payments limited to BRL 20,000. It did not apply, however, if the beneficiary of the payment was a resident of a low-tax jurisdiction or if it benefited from a privileged tax regime.</p>
               <p>For capital gains, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.2.1.">6.2.1.</xref>
               </p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.3.5." label="6.3.5.">
               <title>Withholding tax rates chart</title>
               <include-item collection="wht" src="wht_br.xml"/>
            </section>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7." label="7.">
         <title>Anti-Avoidance</title>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.1." label="7.1.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_2" score="3">Non-Deductible</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_22" score="3">Conduit Companies / Beneficial Ownership</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_3" score="3">Abuse of Law</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_1" score="3">Controlled Foreign Corporations / Anti-Tax Havens [CFCs]</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_2_11" score="3">Final</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_21_11_2" score="3">Non-Deductible</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_22" score="3">Conduit Companies / Beneficial Ownership</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_3" score="3">Abuse of Law</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_1" score="3">Controlled Foreign Corporations / Anti-Tax Havens [CFCs]</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_3_2_11" score="3">Final</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>General</title>
            <p>The main anti-avoidance legislation includes: National Tax Code, Law 9,430 of 27 December 1996, Law 10,451 of 10 May 2002, Law 11,727 of June 2008, Normative Instruction 1,037/2010, Law 12,973 of 13 May 2014, Normative Instruction 1,530/2014, Normative Instruction 1,474/2014, Normative Instruction 1,658/2016, Normative Instruction 1,634/2016 and Normative Instruction 1,683/2016.</p>
            <p>General anti-avoidance rules were introduced for both domestic and international transactions (article 116 of the National Tax Code). They provide that the tax authorities may disregard transactions carried out to conceal taxable events or to modify tax liability. The general anti-avoidance rule requires further regulation by an ordinary law to set conditions, criteria and procedures to be followed by the tax authorities. Such regulation has not yet been enacted.</p>
            <p>Specific anti-avoidance rules apply under Brazilian legislation, i.e. special tax treatment for outbound payments to residents in low-tax jurisdictions, transfer pricing, thin capitalization and CFC rules – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.4.">7.4.</xref>
            </p>
            <topic>
               <title>Special tax treatment for outbound payments to residents in low-tax jurisdictions</title>
               <p>Payments of certain types of income (e.g. interest and royalties) and as capital gains to entities resident in low-tax jurisdictions are currently subject to final withholding tax of 25% (instead of the generally applicable rate). Also, certain tax benefits, which are generally available to non-residents of Brazil are not granted to parties residing or domiciled in low-tax jurisdictions.</p>
               <p>Transactions between a Brazilian resident and a company resident in a low-tax jurisdiction are subject to Brazilian transfer pricing rules – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.4.">7.4.</xref>
               </p>
               <p>For the deductibility of payments made to legal entities located in low-tax jurisdictions, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.3.1.">1.3.3.1.</xref>
               </p>
               <p>Tax authorities are also allowed to examine taxpayers' information in documents, books and registries of financial institutions (including information on deposit accounts and financial investments), provided that a tax audit is ongoing and such information is considered indispensable for the audit. Decree 8,303/2014, published in the Official Gazette of 5 September 2014, included transactions engaged with persons who benefit from a privileged tax regime in the list of situations for which access to information is considered indispensable for the tax audit.</p>
            </topic>
            <topic>
               <title>Low-tax jurisdictions and privileged tax regimes</title>
               <p>Article 24 of Law 9,430/1996 (as amended) defines low-tax jurisdictions as those that do not tax income or levy income tax at a top rate below 20% (17% for countries following international fiscal transparency standards, as defined by Normative Instruction 1,530/2014 of 22 December 2014, amended by Normative Instruction 1,560/2015), or which laws restrict the access to shareholding composition and the beneficial ownership of investments. This definition is valid for the purpose of transfer pricing, thin capitalization rules and also for the purpose of the special tax regime applicable to transactions involving low-tax jurisdictions, whenever the respective legislation makes reference to article 24 of Law 9,430/1996 – some legislation on special tax regime applicable to transactions involving low-tax jurisdictions have their autonomous definition of low tax jurisdiction, which normally do not include jurisdictions which laws restrict access to shareholding composition and the beneficial ownership of investments.</p>
               <p>Law 11,727 of June 2008 introduced the concept of “privileged tax regimes” by adding article 24-A to Law 9,430). This concept was created for the purpose of qualifying new transactions that would be subject to transfer pricing rules. The concept of “privileged tax regime” is not applicable for the purpose of the tax treatment of outbound payments to residents in low-tax jurisdictions, but only for transfer pricing purposes. Later on, the concept of “privileged tax regime” was also used for the purpose of application of thin capitalization rules (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.3.">7.3.</xref>).</p>
               <p>Under article 24-A, “privileged tax regime” is one that:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>does not tax income or taxes it at a top rate lower than 20% (17% for countries following international fiscal transparency standards);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>grants tax advantages to a non-resident entity or individual (i) without the need to carry out substantial economic activity in the country or a particular territory or (ii) is conditioned on the company not exercising any substantial economic activity in the country or a particular territory;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>does not tax or taxes proceeds generated abroad at a top rate lower than 20% (17% for countries following international fiscal transparency standards); or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>does not grant access to information related to the composition of shareholders of legal entities, title or beneficial ownership of earnings attributed to non-residents and to economic transactions performed.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Brazilian Revenue Service has issued administrative rules listing the jurisdictions considered to be low-tax jurisdictions and listing the foreign countries and forms of entities considered to be privileged tax regimes. Under the current listing in Normative Instruction 1,037/2010, as amended the following are considered to be low-tax jurisdictions: American Samoa, Andorra, Anguilla, Antigua and Barbuda, Aruba, the Ascension Islands, the Bahamas, Bahrain, Barbados, Belize, the Bermudas, the British Virgin Islands, Brunei, Campione d’Italia, the Cayman Islands, the Channel Islands (Jersey, Guernsey, Alderney and Sark), the Cook Islands, Curaçao, Cyprus, Djibouti, Dominica, French Polynesia, Gibraltar, Grenada, Hong Kong, Ireland, the Isle of Man, Kiribati, Lebanon, Labuan, Liberia, Liechtenstein, Macau, the Maldives, the Marshall Islands, the Mauricio Islands, Monaco, Montserrat, Nauru, Niue, Norfolk Island, Oman, Panama, the Pitcairn Islands, Queshm Island, Saint Helena, Saint Kitts and Nevis, Saint Lucia, Saint Peter and Miguelão Island, Saint Vincent, Samoa, the Seychelles, Sint Maarten, the Solomon Islands, Swaziland, Tonga, Tristan da Cunha, the Turks and Caicos Islands, the United Arab Emirates, the US Virgin Islands and Vanuatu.</p>
               <p>Under article 2 of Normative Instruction 1,037/2010, the list of privileged tax regimes comprises:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with respect to the legislation of Denmark, the regime applicable to holding companies which do not develop substantial economic activity;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>regarding the Netherlands legislation, the regime applicable to holding companies which do not develop substantial economic activity;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>in relation to the legislation of Iceland, the regime applicable to International Trading Companies (ITC);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>in what concerns the legislation of the United States, the regime applicable to companies incorporated as state Limited Liability Companies (LLC), controlled by non-residents, not subject to the federal income tax;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>regarding the Spanish legislation, the regime applicable to companies incorporated as<emph type="i"> Entidad de Tenencia de Valores Extranjeros</emph> (ETVEs) (<emph type="i">see</emph> “suspension” effect discussed below);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>in connection with the legislation of Malta, the regime applicable to International Trading Companies (ITC) and International Holding Companies (IHC);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with reference to Switzerland, Swiss companies which are incorporated as holding companies, domiciliary companies, auxiliary companies, mixed companies, administrative companies or in any other corporate form via a ruling issued by the local tax authorities and that are subject to a corporate income tax rate lower than 20% (combined federal, cantonal and municipal rate) are considered to be subject to a privileged tax regime;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with reference to Austria, Austrian holding companies which do not develop substantial economic activity (included by Normative Instruction 1,658/2016, amended by Normative Instruction 1,683/2016);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with respect to the legislation of Costa Rica, the Free Zone Regimes (<emph type="i">Regimes de Zonas Francas</emph>);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with respect to the legislation of Portugal, the regime of the International Business Centre of Madeira (<emph type="i">Centro Internacional de Negócios da Madeira</emph>); and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with respect to Singapore: (i) a special rate of tax for a non-resident shipowner or charterer or air transport undertaking; (ii) an exemption and concessionary rate of tax for insurance and reinsurance business; (iii) a concessionary rate of tax for the finance and treasury centre; (iv) a concessionary rate of tax for trustee companies; (v) a concessionary rate of tax for income derived from debt securities; (vi) a concessionary rate of tax for global trading companies and qualifying companies; (vii) a concessionary rate of tax for financial sector incentive companies; (viii) a concessionary rate of tax for provision of processing services for financial institutions; (ix) a concessionary rate of tax for shipping investment managers; (x) a concessionary rate of tax for trust income to which a beneficiary is entitled; (xi) a concessionary rate of tax for leasing of aircraft and aircraft engines; (xii) a concessionary rate of tax for aircraft investment managers; (xiii) a concessionary rate of tax for container investment enterprises; (xiv) a concessionary rate of tax for container investment managers; (xv) a concessionary rate of tax for approved insurance brokers; (xvi) a concessionary rate of tax for income derived from managing a qualifying registered business trust or company; (xvii) a concessionary rate of tax for ship broking and forward freight agreement trading; (xviii) a concessionary rate of tax for shipping-related support services; (xix) a concessionary rate of tax for income derived from managing an approved venture company; and (xx) a concessionary rate of tax for international growth companies.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Normative Instruction 1,037/2010 has not been revised to reflect the new income tax threshold standard (17%) established by Ordinance 488/2014.</p>
               <p>A jurisdiction listed as a low-tax jurisdiction or a privileged tax regime may request a revision of its characterization as a low-tax jurisdiction or a privileged tax regime (currently regulated by Normative Instruction 1,530, which was enacted on 22 December 2014). There may be a suspension of the listing in relation to a certain jurisdiction, at the discretion of the Federal Revenue Service Secretary, while the request is being considered. The decision on the review process has no retroactive effect.</p>
               <p>A request was presented by Spain and suspension was granted through the Normative Act 22 published on 2 December 2010 regarding the regime applicable to the companies incorporated as Spanish foreign participation holding companies (ETVEs).</p>
               <p>Normative Instruction 1,658/2016 clarified that having “substantial economic activity”, for the purposes of the legislation of Denmark and the Netherlands, means that a company has appropriated operational capacity for its purposes, as evidenced, among others factors, by means of having at its disposal (i) a sufficient number of employees to develop its activities, and (ii) the physical facilities for the exercise of its management and decisions related to (a) the development of activities in order to get income derived from its assets, and (b) the administration of equity interest in order to get income arising from the distribution of profit and capital gain.</p>
            </topic>
            <topic>
               <title>Identification of beneficial owner</title>
               <p>Normative Instruction 1,863/2018, published in the Official Gazette of 28 December 2016, introduced a requirement for resident and offshore companies to identify the beneficial owners of their transactions conducted in Brazil. Entities concerned are:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>investment funds and clubs operating under the Securities Commission's (<emph type="i">Comissão de Valores Mobiliários</emph>, CVM) regulations;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>foreign entities either (i) holding real estate, vehicles, vessels, aircraft, bank accounts, investments in financial or capital markets and equity interests in other companies (including other than in the financial market) in Brazil or (ii) performing transactions relating to leasing, chartering of vessels, rental of equipment or simple lease or importation of goods without foreign exchange hedging for the capitalization of companies in Brazil;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>unincorporated joint ventures (<emph type="i">Sociedades em Conta de Participações</emph>) linked to a general partner (<emph type="i">sócio ostensivo</emph>); and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>any other entities that may be of interest to the Federal Revenue Service.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Penalties for not disclosing the beneficial owner include suspension of the taxpayers' registration number (CNPJ) and inability to use bank accounts (except for return of investments to the country or for fulfilling obligations agreed on before the suspension) and financial applications, or to obtain loans.</p>
            </topic>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.2." label="7.2.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="2_16" score="3">Transfer Pricing</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_16_11" score="3">Arm's Length</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_16_12_1" score="3">Comparable Uncontrolled Price [CUP]</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_16_12_2" score="3">Resale Price</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_16_12_3" score="3">Cost-plus</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_16_13_3_3" score="3">TP Methods</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_16_31_1" score="3">Required Documentation</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_16_32_2" score="3">Adjustments</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_6" score="3">Transfer Pricing</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_6_11" score="3">Arm's Length</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_6_12_1" score="3">Comparable Uncontrolled Price [CUP]</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_6_12_2" score="3">Resale Price</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_6_12_3" score="3">Cost-plus</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_6_12" score="3">Methods</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_6_31_1" score="3">Required Documentation</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_6_32_2" score="3">Adjustments</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Transfer pricing</title>
            <p>The main legislation on transfer pricing includes: Law 9,430 of 27 December 1996, Law 12,715 of 17 September 2012, Normative Instruction 1,312/2012, Law 12,766 of 27 December 2012, Normative Instruction 1,322/2012 and Normative Instruction 1,681/2016.</p>
            <p>An OECD-Brazil transfer pricing project is currently ongoing in order to examine the similarities and gaps between the Brazilian and OECD approaches to valuing cross-border transactions between associated firms for tax purposes and assesses the potential for Brazil to move closer to the OECD’s transfer pricing rules. On 11 July 2019, the OECD and Brazil issued a joint statement with an assessment of the strengths and weaknesses of the Brazilian transfer pricing legal and administrative framework. On 18 December 2019, a joint report was issued with proposals for a “full and immediate alignment” and for a “full and gradual alignment” of the Brazilian transfer pricing rules with the OECD standard. A partial alignment was also considered but eventually dismissed by the report as a viable option. </p>
            <p>The transfer pricing rules adopted by Brazil in 1996 – with new rules introduced by Law 12,715/2012 – deviate from the OECD Transfer Pricing Guidelines. Despite basically following the methodology suggested by the OECD Guidelines, Brazilian law adopted fixed margins for the various methods, regardless of the specific situation of the taxpayer or peculiarities of the business. The criteria for searching for and adopting comparables are not clearly regulated. The transfer pricing rules expressly authorize only two comparability factors: specific contractual terms and some differences in characteristics of similar products, services or rights. There is not much leeway for advance pricing agreement (APA) procedures. The related-party test covers various relationships and is not restricted to associated enterprises.</p>
            <p>Transactions between a Brazilian resident company and a company resident in a low-tax jurisdiction or benefiting from a privileged tax regime are subject to Brazilian transfer pricing rules, irrespective of whether the two parties qualify as associated enterprises. For the definition of low-tax jurisdiction for the purpose of transfer pricing rules, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.1.">7.1.</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Brazilian transfer pricing rules currently do not apply to cross-border payments of trademark or patent royalties, nor to fees payable as compensation for the transfer of technology or for the rendering of technical, administrative or scientific assistance services.</p>
            <p>In view of the amendments to Brazilian transfer pricing rules brought by Law 12,715/2012, the federal tax authorities have issued Normative Instruction 1,312/2012, which replaced Normative Instruction 243/2002.</p>
            <p>Under Normative Instruction 1,312/2012, Brazilian transfer pricing rules also apply to back-to-back transactions, described as the ones in which there is no effective import (entry) or export (exit) of the goods and services into and from Brazil, although there is the acquisition and/or sale of goods and services by a Brazilian company with an affiliated entity outside of Brazil.</p>
            <topic>
               <title>Transfer pricing rules for import transactions</title>
               <p>There are four methods for determining the price limit for products, services or rights imported by Brazilian companies from associated enterprises:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>comparable uncontrolled price method (<emph type="i">Preços Independentes Comparados</emph>, PIC) for import transactions. The transfer price is based on the average price of identical or similar products or services in purchase and sale transactions carried out in either the internal or external market under similar payment conditions. Only transactions between unrelated parties are acceptable for comparison. The transactions with non-related parties used for purposes of applying such method must correspond to, at least, 5% of the total value of the import transactions carried out with related parties and subject to transfer pricing control, during the calculation period. They must also correspond to independent prices charged in the same calendar year for the corresponding import transactions subject to transfer pricing control;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>resale price less margin method (<emph type="i">Preço de Revenda Menos Lucro</emph>, PRL). The transfer price is based on the average resale price of the goods applied by the importer in transactions with independent parties, less unconditional discounts, taxes, brokerage fees and profit margin. Margins for the application of the PRL method vary in accordance to the company’s industrial sector (20%, 30% or 40%).</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>cost-plus method (<emph type="i">Custo Produção Mais Lucro</emph>, CPL), with a fixed profit margin of 20%. The transfer price is based on the average production cost of identical or similar products, services or rights in the jurisdiction in which such products, services or rights were originally produced, increased by taxes paid in such jurisdiction and with a fixed profit margin of 20% of the cost net of taxes; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>price under import quotation method (<emph type="i">Preço sob cotação da importação</emph>, PCI), introduced by Law 12,715/2012, and mandatorily applicable to intercompany import transaction of commodities. The benchmark is the daily average values of the quotation of goods or rights subject to public prices on internationally recognized exchange or securities markets, adjusted by the applicable premiums and other variables.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>If more than one method could apply, the company may elect the method resulting in the highest import price.</p>
               <p>If the average price paid by the Brazilian importer exceeds the average price determined under these methods, a transfer pricing adjustment is required and, as a consequence, the excess amount paid will be added to the taxable base of the importer. Conversely, if the average price paid by the Brazilian importer is less than the price determined under Brazilian transfer pricing rules, no tax adjustment is required.</p>
            </topic>
            <topic>
               <title>Transfer pricing rules for export transactions</title>
               <p>Whenever the average sales price of goods, services or rights exported by a Brazilian company in a taxable year is less than 90% of the average sales price of the same goods, services or rights by such company in the domestic market within the same taxable year and under similar payment conditions, the price of those goods, services or rights will be determined by tax authorities under one of the five methods established by Brazilian law. The applicable methods are:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>comparable uncontrolled price method for export transactions (<emph type="i">Preço de Venda nas Exportações</emph>, PVEs). The transfer price is based on the average price of identical or similar services, products or rights exported by a Brazilian company to foreign independent parties in the same taxable year and under similar payment conditions;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>wholesale price in the country of destination, less profit margin method (<emph type="i">Preço de Venda por Atacado no País de Destino Diminuído do Lucro</emph>, PVA), with fixed profit margin of 15%. The transfer price is based on the average sales price of identical or similar products in the wholesale market of the country of destination of the exported products, under similar payment conditions, less local taxes and less a 15% fixed profit margin;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>retail price in the country of destination less profit margin method (<emph type="i">Preço de Venda a Varejo no País de Destino Diminuído do Lucro</emph>, PVV), with a fixed profit margin of 30%. The transfer price is based on the average sales price of identical or similar products in the retail market of the country of destination of the exported products, less taxes and less a 30% fixed profit margin;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>acquisition or production cost, plus taxes and profit margin method (<emph type="i">Custo de Aquisição ou de Produção Mais Tributos e Lucro</emph>, CAP), with a fixed profit margin of 15%. The transfer price is based on the average acquisition or production costs of the exported products, services or rights, increased by Brazilian taxes and with a 15% fixed profit margin, calculated on costs and taxes; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>quota price for exports method (<emph type="i">Preço sob cotação da exportação</emph>, PECEX), introduced by Law 12,715/2012, and mandatorily applicable to intercompany export transaction of commodities. The benchmark is the daily average values of the quotation of goods or rights subject to public prices on internationally recognized exchange or securities markets. In the absence of a trading price in commodities and future exchanges, prices could be compared to those obtained from independent data sources provided by internationally known research institutes.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Brazilian law adopts some safe harbour rules for transfer pricing in relation to export transactions. Under the first general safe harbour rule, which is expressly provided by the law, a taxpayer is deemed to have applied an appropriate transfer price if the average export sales price is at least 90% of the average domestic sales price in the Brazilian market during the same period and on similar payment terms. A second safe harbour rule allows a difference of up to 5% (upwards or downwards), in relation to the overall transactions, and 3% (upwards and downwards), in relation to the transactions subject to the PCI and PECEX methods, between the adjusted-limit price and the transaction price.</p>
               <p>Two other safe harbours aim at simplifying the application of the transfer pricing rules (these two other safe harbours are not considered true safe harbours, because tax authorities remain required to review the transfer pricing methods and may, in principle, assess the taxpayer). These rules allow exporters to demonstrate the appropriateness of their transfer pricing, exclusively on the basis of the export transaction documents, if certain conditions are met. These rules are also not applicable to the transactions subject to the PECEX method.</p>
               <p>If more than one method can be applied, the company may adopt the method which results in the lower export price. If the average price applied by the Brazilian company in its export transactions exceeds the average price obtained under the above-mentioned methods, no adjustment is required. Conversely, if the average price applied by the Brazilian company is lower than the price obtained under the above-mentioned methods, a transfer pricing adjustment is required and the difference will be added to the taxable base.</p>
               <p>Under Administrative Rule 222 (<emph type="i">Portaria</emph> 222), an individual, a corporate taxpayer or a group of taxpayers, such as a trade union or business association can request modifications to the predetermined profit-margins outlined above for transfer pricing purposes. The claim must be supported by relevant documentation, and no request can be made for past taxable periods.</p>
            </topic>
            <topic>
               <title>Transfer pricing rules for cross-border loans</title>
               <topic>
                  <title>Inbound loans</title>
                  <p>Interest payments made to non-resident related parties or to persons located in a low-tax jurisdiction or benefiting from a privileged tax regime are only deductible up to the amount calculated on the basis of the rates established below, in addition to a spread determined by the Brazilian Ministry of Finance (article 249 of Decree 9,580/2018 and article 22 of Law 9,430/1996):</p>
                  <list>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>the rate of Brazilian sovereign bonds issued in USD in foreign markets, in case of transactions in USD, subject to a fixed interest rate;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>the rate of Brazilian sovereign bonds issued in BRL in foreign markets, in case of transactions in BRL, subject to a fixed interest rate; and</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>London Interbank Offered Rate (LIBOR) for a period of 6 months, in all other cases. In addition, section 22 of Law 9,430/1996 expressly provides that the novation, renewal or renegotiation of existing agreements should be considered as a new transaction and, therefore, if any of these acts are carried out from 1 January 2013, the corresponding loan agreement would be subject to the deductibility limitations established by Law 12,766/2012 (and not to the standard LIBOR rate for USD deposits with the 3% spread).</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>Outbound loans</title>
                  <p>In relation to outbound loans, taxpayers are required to recognize for CIT purposes minimum interest revenue, based on the same parameters outlined above, i.e. different rates, based on the characteristics of the transaction, for agreements executed from 1 January 2013.</p>
               </topic>
            </topic>
            <topic>
               <title>Country-by-country (CbC) reporting</title>
               <p>Normative Instruction 1,681/2016 provided for the obligation of the filling in of the CbC report by the final holding of multinational groups which is resident for tax purposes in Brazil and whose economic group has earned consolidated revenues greater than BRL 2.26 billion or EUR 750 million in the fiscal year prior to the fiscal year of the report. Through the CbC reporting, Brazilian Revenue Service has access to information aggregated by each jurisdiction in which the multinational group operates, comprising the following items: (i) consolidated revenues, segregating those obtained in transactions with related and unrelated parties; (ii) income or losses before income tax; (iii) income tax and, in the case of Brazil, also the amount of CSLL paid; (iv) the income tax due; (v) the capital stock; (vi) retained earnings; (vii) the number of employees, workers and other associates; and (viii) tangible assets different than cash and cash equivalents. In addition, the reporting entity shall identify (i) each entity that is a member of the multinational group, its jurisdiction of residence for tax purposes; (ii) the place of incorporation (only when the tax residence does not correspond to the place of incorporation) and (iii) the nature of its main economic activities. </p>
               <p>Multinational companies that are obliged to fill in the CbC report must provide information from the economic group to the Brazilian Revenue Service, who will exchange this information with the other countries under the Multilateral Agreement of Competent Authority Agreement on the Exchange of Country-by-Country Reports (signed on 21 October 2016). On 20 July 2017, Brazil and the United States also concluded a bilateral competent authority agreement for the exchange of CbC reports. On 27 November 2018, the tax authorities initiated the exchange of CbC reports with other jurisdictions.</p>
            </topic>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.3." label="7.3.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_2" score="3">Thin Capitalization [Thin Cap]</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_2" score="3">Thin Capitalization [Thin Cap]</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Limitations on interest deductibility</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.3.1." label="7.3.1.">
               <title>This capitalization</title>
               <p>The main legislation on thin capitalization includes Law 12,249 of 11 June 2010 and Normative Instruction 1,154/2011.</p>
               <p>With effect from 15 December 2009 <emph type="i">thin capitalization rules </emph>were introduced in the Brazilian legal framework, aiming at limiting the deductibility for corporate income taxes purposes of interest paid to foreign related parties, residents of low-tax jurisdictions or non-residents benefiting from privileged tax regimes (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.1.">7.1.</xref>).</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,249/2010, interest paid by a Brazilian subsidiary to a foreign related party neither located in a low-tax jurisdiction nor subject to a privileged tax regime may be deducted for corporate income taxes purposes only if the interest expense is necessary for the company’s activities and the following thresholds are met:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the value of the debt granted by the foreign investor does not exceed twice the value of the equity stake held by the investor in the equity of the Brazilian subsidiary (debt lower than 200% of investment equity value); and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the overall indebtedness of the Brazilian subsidiary does not exceed twice the value of the equity stake held by all related parties in the equity of the Brazilian subsidiary (total indebtedness less than 200% of related-party investment equity value).</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>If the debt payable to the foreign investor exceeds the ratios above, the excess interest expense payable by the Brazilian subsidiary is not deductible for the purposes of corporate income taxes. There is no re-characterization of interest as dividend.</p>
               <p>Interest payable by a Brazilian company to a foreign creditor (related or not) domiciled in a low-tax jurisdiction or benefiting from a “privileged tax regime” (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.1.">7.1.</xref>) may be deducted for the purposes of corporate income taxes only if the interest expense is necessary for the company’s activities and the amount of the Brazilian company’s indebtedness to all entities located in low-tax jurisdictions or benefiting from “privileged tax regimes” does not exceed 30% of the equity of the Brazilian borrower.</p>
               <p>If the debt payable to the foreign creditor exceeds the ratios above, the excess interest expense incurred by the Brazilian subsidiary is not deductible. There is no re-characterization of interest as dividend.</p>
               <p>Normative Instruction 1,154/2011 clarified that the thin capitalization rules also apply to transactions where a non-related financial institution is used as an intermediary between the Brazilian company and its related party domiciled abroad. On the other hand, loan transactions entered into between two Brazilian related companies are not subject to thin capitalization rules, even if the guarantor, attorney-in-fact or any intervening party is a related party domiciled abroad or a resident of a low-tax jurisdiction or of a country which provides for a privileged tax regime.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.3.2." label="7.3.2.">
               <title>Limitation on the deductibility of interest on net equity</title>
               <p>Interest on equity is a special type of payment to shareholders, calculated on the company’s equity accounts, applying the central bank’s long-term interest rate. The interest deductible for CIT purposes is subject to two different limitations. The first one refers to the amount payable as interest on net equity. Accordingly, such amount must be determined based on the pro rata variation of the TJLP (long-term interest rate published by the Central Bank of Brazil) applied to the equity accounts of the corporate taxpayer (share capital, capital reserve, profits reserves, treasury stock and accumulated losses). The second limitation is the amount of interest on net equity expense that may be actually deducted. This amount is limited to the higher of (i) 50% of the current year’s net profit, or (ii) 50% of the accumulated profits or profits reserves. </p>
               <p>The general limitation applicable to outbound remittances made from Brazil to persons located in a low-tax jurisdiction or benefiting from a privileged tax regime (i.e. deductibility conditioned to the fulfilment of certain requirements – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_1.3.3.1.">1.3.3.1.</xref>) is not applicable to interest on net equity.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.3.3." label="7.3.3.">
               <title>Limitation on deductibility of interest under transfer pricing rules </title>
               <p>For limitation on deductibility of interest payments made to non-resident related parties or to persons located in a low-tax jurisdiction or benefiting from a privileged tax regime, <emph type="i">see </emph>section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.2.">7.2.</xref>
               </p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.4." label="7.4.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_1" score="3">Controlled Foreign Corporations / Anti-Tax Havens [CFCs]</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="2_14_12" score="3">Controlled Foreign Corporations / Anti-Tax Haven [CFCs]</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_31_2_1" score="3">Controlled Foreign Corporations / Anti-Tax Havens [CFCs]</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_1_42_12" score="3">Controlled Foreign Corporations / Anti-Tax Haven [CFCs]</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Controlled foreign company</title>
            <p>The main legislation on controlled foreign company includes: Provisional Measure 2,158-35 of 24 August of 2001, Law 12,973 of 13 May 2014 and Normative Instruction 1,674/2016.</p>
            <p>Pursuant to article 74 of Provisional Measure 2,158-35/2001, Brazil imposes taxation on undistributed profits derived by foreign controlled or affiliated companies of Brazilian resident entities. Brazil’s CFC rules apply only to resident companies (not to resident individuals).</p>
            <p>A controlled company is one in which the investor holds, directly or via related parties, rights that assure, on a permanent basis, the power to elect the majority of the directors and to prevail in corporate decisions. Affiliated companies are those in which the investor has significant influence, considered as the power to take part in the definition of the company’s financial and operating policy, without having control of the company. A presumed significant influence is when the investor owns 20% or more of the shares of the company, without having control.</p>
            <p>Under Brazilian CFC rules in force until 2014, profits derived by all foreign controlled or affiliated companies of Brazilian resident entities, irrespective of whether their profits arise from active or passive activities, were converted into BRL and added to the results of the Brazilian legal entity on 31 December of each year in proportion to the ownership percentage, regardless of actual distribution.</p>
            <p>On 10 April 2013, the Supreme Federal Court (<emph type="i">Supremo Tribunal Federal</emph>) ruled that Brazilian CFC rules were unconstitutional in regard to foreign affiliated companies located outside a low-tax jurisdiction. The court confirmed, however, the constitutionality of Brazilian CFC rules in regard to foreign controlled companies located in low-tax jurisdictions. The decision, given in the Direct Action of Unconstitutionality 2,588, is binding on all taxpayers. As a consequence, Brazilian CFC rules no longer apply to foreign affiliated companies located outside a low-tax jurisdiction. The rules remain applicable to foreign affiliated companies located in a low-tax jurisdiction (judged constitutional) and to foreign controlled companies located outside a low-tax jurisdiction (in this case because the court did not reach a decision on the constitutionality of Brazilian CFC rules) (<emph type="i">see</emph> BR: SFC, 10 Apr. 2013, 2,588, Case Law IBFD).</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, in the judgement of Extraordinary Appeal 541,090 on the same day, the Supreme Federal Court confirmed the constitutionality of Brazilian CFC rules in regard to foreign controlled companies located outside a low-tax jurisdiction. The decision is however not binding on all taxpayers, but establishes case law on the matter (<emph type="i">see</emph> BR: SFC, 10 Apr. 2013, 2,588, Case Law IBFD).</p>
            <p>On 13 May 2014, Law 12,973/14 introduced significant changes to the Brazilian CFC rules in order to adjust them in accordance with the Supreme Court decision. These changes entered into force on 1 January 2015 (taxpayers could, however, opt to implement the new CFC rules for the calendar year 2014). Unlike the previous CFC legislation, the new rules introduced by Law 12,973/2014 provide distinct tax treatments for controlled and affiliated entities (<emph type="i">see</emph> below).</p>
            <p>Until 31 December 2019, an exemption, i.e. a carve-out from the CFC regime, was provided to profits earned by (direct or indirect) controlled subsidiaries or affiliated companies in connection with certain activities (e.g. freight, leasing, rent and provision of services directly related to exploration and exploitation of oil and natural gas in Brazil). Therefore, such profits were not included in the taxable base of the parent company resident in Brazil, provided that certain conditions were met.</p>
            <topic>
               <title>Foreign controlled companies</title>
               <p>The new rules regarding controlled companies have not changed significantly. Profits derived by all (direct and indirect) foreign controlled companies owned by Brazilian companies continue to be subject to automatic taxation in Brazil on their pro-rata share, irrespective of the jurisdiction in which the controlled company is located, and regardless of whether the profits are legally or economically available to the Brazilian company.</p>
               <p>An ordinary foreign tax credit is available against the tax on profit distributions, if any, as well as an indirect credit for the underlying tax paid by the distributing subsidiary in the foreign jurisdiction. Excess credit may be carried forward indefinitely.</p>
               <p>The positive result of each controlled foreign entity is added to the results of the Brazilian company while the losses of each entity may only be offset against the positive results of each controlled foreign entity. However, until 2022, and provided certain conditions are met, controlling entities in Brazil may benefit from a credit in the amount of 9% of the positive result related to investments in foreign entities which are engaged in certain activities (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.4.">6.1.4.</xref>).</p>
               <p>Until 2022, and provided certain conditions are met, the positive and negative results (excluding foreign exchange results) of foreign entities controlled by Brazilian companies can be consolidated in Brazil by the parent company. For details, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_6.1.2.">6.1.2.</xref>
               </p>
               <p>Provided that certain conditions are met, the Brazilian parent company may elect to pay the CIT due annually, as a lump-sum, or in instalments to be paid within 8 years – the first instalment must amount to 12.5% of the tax due. The unpaid tax is adjusted for interest and foreign exchange fluctuations.</p>
               <p>According to Provisional Measure 795/2017, profits derived from the activities of freight, leasing, rent, and provision of services related to exploration and exploitation of oil and gas by directly and indirectly controlled foreign companies and affiliated foreign companies, are excluded from the Brazilian company taxable basis.</p>
            </topic>
            <topic>
               <title>Foreign affiliated companies</title>
               <p>In relation to the affiliated companies, Law 12,973/2014 introduced significant changes. Previous to Law 12,973/2014, affiliated companies were automatically subject to taxation under general CFC rules. Under the new CFC rules, affiliated companies are, in principle, not subject to automatic taxation in Brazil (i.e. profits are taxed only when credited or paid as specified in Law 12,973/2014). However, these new rules only apply if the affiliated company:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>is not (or is not directly or indirectly controlled by an entity) subject to a tax regime with a nominal income tax rate lower than 20% (the so-called “under-taxation” regime (<emph type="i">regime de subtributação</emph>)); and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>is not located in a low-tax jurisdiction and does not benefit from a privileged tax regime.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>If one of the conditions listed above is not met, the same rules apply to controlled foreign entities.</p>
               <p>Even though affiliated companies are not, as a rule, subject to automatic taxation in Brazil, resident companies may submit the profits derived by the affiliated foreign companies to the same regime applicable to the profits of controlled companies. This is regulated by Normative Instruction 1,674/2016.</p>
            </topic>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.5." label="7.5.">
            <title>Other anti-avoidance rules</title>
            <p>For the special tax treatment for outbound payments to residents in low-tax jurisdictions and identification of beneficial owner, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_7.1.">7.1.</xref>
            </p>
            <p>There are no other anti-avoidance rules.</p>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8." label="8.">
         <taxtopics>
            <taxtopic tc="1_4" score="3">VAT</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <taxtopics version="3.0">
            <taxtopic tc="1_7" score="3">VAT</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <title>Value Added Tax</title>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.1." label="8.1.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_3_1" score="3">Concept of Goods</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_3_2" score="3">Concept of Services</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_3_11" score="3">Imports</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_3_13" score="3">Exports</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_3_1" score="3">Concept of Goods</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_3_2" score="3">Concept of Services</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_3_11" score="3">Imports</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_3_13" score="3">Exports</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>General</title>
            <p>Brazil has two value added taxes. The tax on manufactured products (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre Produtos Industrializados</emph>, IPI) is levied at a federal level on every stage of the producing process and on import transactions. In addition, the tax on the sale of goods, interstate and inter-municipal transportation and on communication services (ICMS) is levied at the state level. Services other than those taxed by ICMS are subject to a municipal tax on services (ISS), which is not a value added tax. For ISS, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.1.">9.6.1.</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Constitutional Amendment 18 of 1 December 1965 replaced the old cumulative tax on sales and the consumption tax on goods, as of 1 January 1966, by taxes on production and consumption (i.e. currently IPI and ICMS).</p>
            <p>IPI and ICMS systems are not part of a bilateral or multilateral harmonization agreement.</p>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.1.1." label="8.1.1.">
               <title>Federal tax on manufactured products (IPI)</title>
               <p>The tax on manufactured products (IPI) is a federal tax levied on the manufacture of products and the import of goods from abroad. Tax rates vary considerably depending on the nature of the product, its tax classification and in line with the constitutional principles of necessity and selectivity (i.e. basic products are generally subject to a lower IPI rate).</p>
               <p>The imposition of IPI follows the VAT input deduction system (in Brazil known as the non-cumulative principle), under which the tax due in prior transactions (including import of products) may be offset against the tax due on subsequent transactions carried out by the manufacturer.</p>
               <p>IPI is mainly governed by Decree 7,212/2010. The Brazilian Revenue Service (<emph type="i">Receita Federal do Brasil</emph>, RFB) is in charge of the administration and collection of IPI.</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,741/2012, companies are required to specify on invoices and receipts the taxes charged (percentages), which are part of the total product sale price or the provision of services, including IPI. Companies must list the municipal, state and federal taxes levied for each product described in invoices and receipts. Alternatively, such information could be displayed on a panel in plain view within their establishments. Companies failing to comply with the requirements of Law 12,741/2012 are subject to administrative penalties.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.1.2." label="8.1.2.">
               <title>State tax on sale of goods, interstate and inter-municipal transportation and communication services (ICMS)</title>
               <p>The ICMS is a type of value-added tax levied by states on the sale of goods, the provision of interstate and intermunicipal transport services and communication services. ICMS is also levied on the import of goods.</p>
               <p>The imposition of ICMS follows the VAT input deduction system (in Brazil known as the non-cumulative principle), under which the tax due in prior transactions (including import of products) may be offset against the tax due on subsequent transactions.</p>
               <p>ICMS is regulated by legislation issued by each state within the limits defined by the Constitution. The finance departments of states (<emph type="i">Secretarias da Fazenda</emph>) are in charge of the administration and collection of ICMS.</p>
               <p>Under specific agreements (<emph type="i">Convênios</emph>) between the states of the Brazilian Federation, states may grant ICMS exemptions, reductions of the taxable base, presumed credits and other tax benefits.</p>
               <p>Each state legislation may establish substitution tax regimes for the collection of ICMS, in which case the taxes imposed on previous or subsequent transactions in the supply chain shall be collected by a single taxpayer.</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,741/2012, companies are required to specify on invoices and receipts the taxes charged (percentages), which are part of the total product sale price or the provision of services, including ICMS. Companies must list the municipal, state and federal taxes levied for each product described in invoices and receipts. Alternatively, such information could also be displayed on a panel in plain view within their establishments. Companies failing to comply with the requirements of Law 12,741/2012 are subject to administrative penalties.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.2." label="8.2.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_2" score="3">Taxable Persons</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_2_12" score="3">Fixed Establishments</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_2_21" score="3">Small Businesses</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_2" score="3">Taxable Persons</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_2_12" score="3">Fixed Establishments</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Taxable persons</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.2.1." label="8.2.1.">
               <title>Federal tax on manufactured products (IPI)</title>
               <p>As a general rule, taxable persons are domestic manufacturers and importers of goods. Suppliers and dealers of goods seized or abandoned and taken to auction are also taxable persons for the purposes of IPI. Private individuals are generally not considered to be taxable persons for the purposes of IPI.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.2.2." label="8.2.2.">
               <title>State tax on sale of goods, interstate and inter-municipal transportation and communication services (ICMS)</title>
               <p>Anyone who frequently and with a commercial purpose acts as a supplier of goods or a provider of interstate and inter-municipal transportation (transportation between Brazilian states and municipalities) or communication, even if the supplies were initiated abroad, are considered taxpayers for the purpose of ICMS.</p>
               <p>As such, a taxable person will be any person that has as its main activity the supply of goods or the provision of the services mentioned. A company or individual that does not have such activities as its main business should not be considered as a taxable person for ICMS purposes.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.3." label="8.3.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_3" score="3">Taxable Events</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_3_11" score="3">Imports</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_3_21_1" score="3">Goods</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_3" score="3">Taxable Events</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_3_11" score="3">Imports</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_3_21_1" score="3">Goods</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Taxable events</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.3.1." label="8.3.1.">
               <title>Federal tax on manufactured products (IPI)</title>
               <p>The taxable transactions are supplies by manufacturers and importation by any person of any kind of manufactured products. The levy of IPI on the resale of imported goods carried out by the importer was considered constitutional by the Federal Supreme Court in a decision issued on 21 August 2020.</p>
               <p>For the purposes of IPI, manufactured products are those which have been subject to a manufacturing process.</p>
               <p>Under the law, manufacturing processes include:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>transformation of raw material or intermediate products into a new product;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>improvement of the function, use, or appearance of existing products;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>assembly of separate parts to make a new product or separate unit;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>packing of finished products in sales containers not destined merely for transportation; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>renovation of used or deteriorated products to make them serviceable.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The import of products that are exempt from customs duties is also exempt from IPI.</p>
               <p>Under Law 9,000 of 16 March 1995, the import of listed types of equipment, tools and machines is exempt from IPI.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.3.2." label="8.3.2.">
               <title>State tax on the sale of goods, interstate and inter-municipal transport and communication services (ICMS)</title>
               <p>ICMS is on the sale of goods, the provision of interstate and inter-municipal transport services and communication services. ICMS is also levied on the import of goods. Services that are provided together with the sale of goods may be subject to ICMS, provided that such services are not taxed by the ISS.</p>
               <p>Some transactions are treated as taxable supplies, for example:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>consignment and transfers of goods, as well as sales;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the transfer of goods from one establishment to another of the same taxpayer, provided that such establishments are located in different states; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the transfer of fixed assets which have been used for less than 12 months, except when the assets are returned to the establishment of origin or to another establishment pertaining to the same owner.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.4." label="8.4.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_6" score="3">Taxable Amount</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_6_1_1" score="3">Elements to be Included</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_6_1_2" score="3">Elements to be Excluded</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_6" score="3">Taxable Amount</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_6_1_1" score="3">Elements to be Included</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_6_1_2" score="3">Elements to be Excluded</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Taxable amount</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.4.1." label="8.4.1.">
               <title>Federal tax on manufactured products (IPI)</title>
               <p>The taxable amount for IPI purposes is:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with respect to imports, the customs value, as increased by customs duties and any other entry levy imposed on imported goods;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with respect to supplies, the total consideration received or to be received for the supply including incidental charges and ICMS. However, incidental transportation and insurance costs may be excluded from the taxable value provided that they are invoiced separately; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>with respect to manufacturing entrusted to another taxpayer, the price of the transaction as increased by the value of raw materials, intermediary products and packing material provided by the principal.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>On 4 September 2014, the Supreme Federal Court confirmed that the IPI must be levied on the actual value of the purchase operation – that is, taking into account unconditional discounts offered at the time of the sale to exclude the related amount from the taxable base of IPI – and not on the listed price of the product.</p>
               <p>The exclusion of unconditional discounts of the calculation basis of IPI was also reinforced by Federal Senate Resolution 1/2017.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.4.2." label="8.4.2.">
               <title>State tax on the sale of goods, interstate and inter-municipal transport and communication services (ICMS)</title>
               <p>As a general rule, the taxable base for ICMS is the price of the goods or services rendered, increased by the ICMS due (pursuant to gross-up mechanism).</p>
               <p>In respect of imports, the taxable amount is the customs value, as increased by IPI, customs duties and any other entry levy imposed on imported goods (excluding ICMS).</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.5." label="8.5.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_7" score="3">Rates</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_7_1" score="3">Standard</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_7_2" score="3">Reduced</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_7_3" score="3">Increased</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_7" score="3">Rates</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_7_1" score="3">Standard</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_7_2" score="3">Reduced</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_7_3" score="3">Increased</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Rates</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.5.1." label="8.5.1.">
               <title>Federal tax on manufactured products (IPI)</title>
               <p>IPI rates are specified in a lengthy tariff (similar to the customs tariff) Decree 8,950/2016.</p>
               <p>Rates vary inversely with the need for the product (from 300% to nil) and are subject to frequent amendments; thus, non-essential goods (e.g. manufactured tobacco, alcoholic beverages) are subject to high rates while certain semi-manufactured products attract very low rates. A nil rate is applicable, in general, to products considered by the government as essential. Some goods are subject to ad rem rates, based on fixed values.</p>
               <p>In view of the COVID-19 pandemic, the IPI rate levied on the production of listed medical supplies has been temporarily reduced to 0% (until 1 January 2021).</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.5.2." label="8.5.2.">
               <title>State tax on the sale of goods, interstate and inter-municipal transport and communication services (ICMS)</title>
               <p>For domestic transactions within a state, the applicable tax rates are determined by the relevant state (in accordance with the limits established by the federal senate). The general and maximum rates applicable in Brazilian states are the following:</p>
               <table>
                  <tgroup cols="3">
                     <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2120*"/>
                     <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2140*"/>
                     <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="2140*"/>
                     <thead>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>State</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>General rate (%)</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>Maximum rate (%)</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                     </thead>
                     <tbody>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Acre</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>33</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Alagoas </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>25</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Amapá</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>29</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Amazonas </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>30</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Bahia</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>38</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Ceará</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>28</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Distrito Federal</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>35</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Espírito Santo</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>27</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Goiás</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>29</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Maranhão</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>27</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Mato Grosso</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>35</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Mato Grosso do Sul</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>28</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Minas Gerais</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>31</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Pará</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>30</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Paraíba </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>35</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Paraná</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>29</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Pernambuco</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>30</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Piauí </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>30</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Rio de Janeiro </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>25</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Rio Grande do Norte </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>28</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Rio Grande do Sul </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>25</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Rondônia</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17.5</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>37</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Roraima </p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>25</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Santa Catarina</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>17</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>25</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>São Paulo</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>25</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Sergipe</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>30</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry colname="col1">
                              <p>Tocantins</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col2">
                              <p>18</p>
                           </entry>
                           <entry colname="col3">
                              <p>27</p>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                     </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
               </table>
               <p>As a rule, interstate transactions between ICMS taxpayers are subject to rates of 7% or 12%, depending on the states involved. Federal Senate Resolution 22/89 provides that the general rate applicable for interstate transaction is 12%, but the 7% rate is applicable on interstate transactions carried out from states in the South and Southeast (except those made to the State of Espírito Santo) to states in the North, Northeast, Midwest and the State of Espírito Santo. In April 2012, the Brazilian Senate issued Resolution 13/12, which unified the ICMS rate applicable to interstate transactions involving imported goods. In those situations, from 1 January 2013, the ICMS is imposed at a 4% rate (before 1 January 2013, the 7% or 12% rate generally applied to interstate transactions). The single 4% rate applies to: (i) simple resale of goods after their import (i.e. without going through any industrial process) and (ii) goods subject to any manufacturing process resulting in other goods or merchandises with over 40% of imported content (the percentage is based on the ratio between the prices of imported products and the value of the interstate transaction).</p>
               <p>Transactions involving natural gas and products without domestic manufacturing are excluded from applying the 4% rate. The products deemed as "without domestic manufacturing" are defined by federal legislation.</p>
               <p>Until 31 December 2015, the interstate sale of goods to final consumers was subject to ICMS in the state of origin at the applicable internal rate. Since 1 January 2016, the ICMS is shared between the state of origin and the state of destination as follows:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the state of origin charges ICMS at the interstate rate; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>ICMS at a rate resulting from the difference between the interstate rate and the internal rate is charged and shared in the following proportions:</p>
                     <list>
                        <item label="-">
                           <p>40% for the state of destination and 60% for the state of origin in 2016;</p>
                        </item>
                        <item label="-">
                           <p>60% for the state of destination and 40% for the state of origin in 2017;</p>
                        </item>
                        <item label="-">
                           <p>80% for the state of destination and 20% for the state of origin in 2018; and</p>
                        </item>
                        <item label="-">
                           <p>100% for the state of destination in 2019 onwards.</p>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Federal states are allowed to impose ICMS on standardized digital goods that are sold to or imported by final consumers and delivered through electronic means (e.g. software download, streaming and cloud computing) at the rate of 5%.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.6." label="8.6.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_8" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_8" score="3">Exemptions</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Exemptions</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.6.1." label="8.6.1.">
               <title>Federal tax on manufactured products (IPI)</title>
               <p>Exempt activities include:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>preparation of food and refreshments that are sold directly to the consumer without special containers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>production of handcrafts by artisans in their own dwellings without the cooperation of other persons and sold directly by the artisan to the consumer;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>production of clothes and similar articles by independent workers under a direct deal with the consumer;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the preparation of products directly ordered by the consumer or user, provided that professional work is preponderant in the preparation;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>medicines prepared in a pharmacy and sold directly to the consumer; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>other specific exemptions under tax incentives or as a strategy of the government to promote the economic growth by the reduction of final consumer prices.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.6.2." label="8.6.2.">
               <title>State tax on the sale of goods, interstate and inter-municipal transport and communication services (ICMS)</title>
               <p>Under the applicable laws, some transactions are not subject to ICMS, including export of goods and services, and transactions concerning gold, books, newspapers and periodicals. According to a decision of the Federal Supreme Court issued on 8 March 2017 in Extraordinary Appeals 330.817 and 595.676, the constitutional tax exemption for books, newspapers, periodicals and the paper used for printing also covers e-books and e-readers.</p>
               <p>There are other transactions which are deemed not to be taxable events for ICMS purposes or which are not subject to ICMS under precedents issued by Brazilian courts. In this regard, on 12 September 2014 the Supreme Federal Court confirmed that ICMS is not levied on the import of goods under leasing arrangements.</p>
               <p>It is common that state tax authorities grant tax incentives for the total or partial reduction of the tax burden imposed on the import or sale of products. The activities and products benefited by these tax incentives and the requirements to the enjoyment of them depend on each state.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.7." label="8.7.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_4_2_31" score="3">Non-Residents</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_7_2_31" score="3">Non-Residents</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Non-residents</title>
            <p>Non-residents are not subject to IPI or ICMS.</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.8." label="8.8.">
            <title>Other</title>
            <p>There are no other value added taxes in Brazil.</p>
         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9." label="9.">
         <taxtopics>
            <taxtopic tc="1_5" score="3">Other Taxes</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <taxtopics version="3.0">
            <taxtopic tc="1_10" score="3">Other Taxes</taxtopic>
         </taxtopics>
         <title>Miscellaneous Taxes</title>
         <p>Resident companies (as well as non-resident persons with a taxable presence in Brazil) are liable to all miscellaneous taxes. Non-resident persons with no taxable presence in Brazil are liable to municipal tax on real estate transfer (<emph type="i">see</emph> section<xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.2.1."> 9.2.1.</xref>), municipal tax on service (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.1.">9.6.1.</xref>) and to a tax on financial transactions (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.2.">9.6.2.</xref>).</p>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.1." label="9.1.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_2" score="3">Capital / Property Taxes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_3" score="3">Capital Contribution</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_2" score="3">Capital / Property Taxes</taxtopic>
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_3" score="3">Capital Contribution</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Capital duty</title>
            <p>There is no capital duty in Brazil. However, the inflow of funds to Brazil may trigger a tax on financial transactions, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.2.">9.6.2.</xref>
            </p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.2." label="9.2.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_1" score="3">Transfer Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_1" score="3">Transfer Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Transfer tax</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.2.1." label="9.2.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_1_13" score="3">Immovable PropertyTransfer Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_1_13" score="3">Immovable PropertyTransfer Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Immovable property</title>
               <p>The municipal tax on real estate transfer (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre a Transmissão de Bens Imóveis</emph>, ITBI) is levied on the inter vivos transfer of real estate as well as the transfer or assignment of in rem rights on real estate and the assignment of rights for the acquisition of real estate.</p>
               <p>ITBI is not levied on the transfer of assets or rights thereto in the case of a capital contribution, nor on the transfer of assets or rights resulting from a merger, consolidation, spin-off or liquidation, unless the prevailing activity of the company receiving the asset or right is (i) the purchase and sale or (ii) rental or leasing of real estate.</p>
               <p>The ITBI rate is established by the applicable municipal law (several municipalities apply a 2% rate), and no limits are imposed by the Constitution. The taxable base is the value established by the municipality, taking into account (i) the fair market value of the assets or rights or (ii) the transaction value, whichever is higher. The seller or purchaser (according to the laws of the municipality) is liable for the collection of the tax.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.2.2." label="9.2.2.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_1_11" score="3">Share Transfer Taxes</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_45_1" score="3">Financial Transaction Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_1_11" score="3">Share Transfer Taxes</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_45" score="3">Financial Transaction Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Shares, bonds and other securities</title>
               <p>There is no transfer tax on the transfer of shares, bonds and other securities. However some transactions (including transfers) involving shares, bonds and other securities may be subject to a tax on financial transactions – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.2.">9.6.2.</xref>
               </p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.2.3." label="9.2.3.">
               <title>Other</title>
               <p>There are no other transfer taxes.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.3." label="9.3.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_1_2" score="3">Stamp Duties / Documentary Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_1_2" score="3">Stamp Duties / Documentary Taxes</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Stamp duty</title>
            <p>There is no stamp duty in Brazil.</p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.4." label="9.4.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_21" score="3">Customs Duties</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_21" score="3">Customs Duties</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Customs duty</title>
            <p>The import duty is a federal duty imposed upon the import of products manufactured abroad and brought into Brazil. As a general rule, the return of domestic products to the Brazilian market is not subject to this tax. The import duty rates may be changed by the executive branch.</p>
            <p>The import duty is imposed on the CIF value of the imported product. In general, the taxable base of the import duty is defined under the rules in the Customs Pricing Agreement that Brazil joined pursuant to section VII of the GATT. The import duty rate levied on listed medical supplies imported to combat the COVID-19 pandemic has been temporarily reduced to 0% (until 31 December 2020). The export tax is also a federal duty. The tax rates may change in accordance with criteria determined by the federal government, within the limits determined by previous law. Currently, however, the export duty is reduced to a zero rate in connection with almost all products.</p>
            <p>For PIS and COFINS contributions levied on imports, <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_3.">3.</xref>
            </p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.5." label="9.5.">
            <taxtopics>
               <taxtopic tc="1_5_22" score="3">Excise Duties</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <taxtopics version="3.0">
               <taxtopic tc="1_10_22" score="3">Excise Duties</taxtopic>
            </taxtopics>
            <title>Excise duty</title>
            <p>There is no excise tax as so defined. However, the tax on manufactured products (IPI) also plays the role of an excise duty for certain products – <emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.">8.</xref>
            </p>
         </section>
         <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6." label="9.6.">
            <title>Other taxes</title>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.1." label="9.6.1.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_32" score="3">Service Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_32" score="3">Service Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Municipal tax on services</title>
               <p>The municipal tax on services (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre Serviços de Qualquer Natureza</emph>, ISS) applies to services of any nature, with the exception of communication services and intra-state and interstate transportation services, which are subject to ICMS (<emph type="i">see</emph> section <xref target="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_8.">8.</xref>). Services provided by non-residents to residents are also subject to ISS. The export of services is not subject to ISS, provided certain conditions are fulfilled.</p>
               <p>The taxpayer is the service provider. In case of import of services, the taxpayer is the non-resident person providing the service. However, Complementary Law 116/2003 allows municipalities to determine by municipal law another person as the responsible for the payment of the tax.</p>
               <p>Municipalities are free to determine the ISS tax rate subject, however, to the tax rates specified by the Federal Constitution and also by a federal complementary law (between 2% and 5%). The scope of taxable services varies from municipality to municipality. Municipalities are only authorized to impose the municipal service tax on the services expressly listed by a federal complementary law (the taxable services list) and reproduced by the relevant municipal law. The taxable base is the price of the services. In the case of services involving the supply of goods, the price of the goods is excluded from the ISS taxable base only if the legislation expressly provides it.</p>
               <p>As a general rule, ISS is collected by the municipality in which the service provider is located. However, according the Complementary Law 157/2016, in the case of construction works, health insurance services, administration of credit and debit cards, leasing, franchising and factoring (and other specific listed services), the tax must be paid to the municipality in which the services are rendered, e.g. the municipality in which the customer or work site is located, the place of the point of sale with a credit/debit card machine, etc.</p>
               <p>Nonetheless, the STF suspended the effects of Complementary Law 157/2016, due to the difficulty in law enforcement and conflicts of jurisdiction between municipalities, which defies the constitutional principle of legal certainty.</p>
               <p>On 24 September 2020, Complementary Law 175/2020 established that for the services of health assistance plans, veterinary assistance plans, fund management, consortium, credit and debit cards and leasing, the ISS must be paid to the municipality in which the customer is located. Differently from Complementary Law 157/2016, there will be a gradual implementation of Complementary Law 175/2020 rules. From 2021 to 2023, the ISS collected will be split between the municipality where the service provider is located and the municipality where the customer is located. From 2023 onwards, the ISS will be entirely allocated to the municipality where the customer is located.</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,741/2012, companies are required to specify on invoices and receipts the taxes charged (percentages), which are part of the total amount of the product sale price or the provision of services, including ISS. In this sense, companies must list the amount of municipal, state and federal taxes levied for each product described in the invoices and receipts. Alternatively, such information could also be displayed on a panel in plain view within their establishments. Companies failing to comply with the requirements of Law 12,741/2012 are subject to administrative penalties.</p>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.2." label="9.6.2.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_45_1" score="3">Financial Transaction Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_45" score="3">Financial Transaction Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Tax on exchange, credit, insurance and securities transactions – tax on financial transactions</title>
               <p>The tax on financial transactions (<emph type="i">Imposto sobre Operações Financeiras</emph>, IOF) is a federal tax levied mainly on currency exchange, credit and insurance transactions and transactions involving securities. The IOF is not subject to the legality principle (which requires changes to be implemented by law), which means that the executive branch may change the IOF tax rate at any time through a decree, provided that the rate does not exceed 25%.</p>
               <p>The IOF is currently regulated by Decree 6,306/07, as amended.</p>
               <p>According to Law 12,741/2012, companies are required to specify on invoices and receipts the taxes charged (percentages) on the sale of goods or the provision of services, including IOF. Companies must list the municipal, state and federal taxes levied for each product described in the invoices and receipts. Alternatively, such information could be displayed on a panel in plain view within their establishments. Companies failing to comply with the requirements of Law 12,741/2012 are subject to administrative penalties.</p>
               <topic>
                  <title>Currency exchange transactions</title>
                  <p>Exchange transactions undertaken with regard to inflows of funds to Brazil and the outflows of funds from Brazil were subject to IOF at a maximum 25% rate.</p>
                  <p>Most transactions are subject to a 0.38% rate. Some transactions benefit from a 0% rate while other transactions have more burdensome taxation (e.g. 1.1%, 6% or 6.38% rate).</p>
                  <p>Currently, a 0% rate applies to a number of foreign exchange transactions, including those for the purpose of inflow and outflow of funds connected to cross-border loans to Brazilian borrowers with an average term exceeding 180 days, of return on investments and earnings, including dividends and interest on equity, return to investors of the funds related to investments in Brazilian financial and capital markets, etc.</p>
                  <p>The Brazilian Federal Government is allowed to increase the IOF rate at any time up to 25%. However, any increase in rates may only apply to future transactions.</p>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>Credit transactions</title>
                  <p>Currently, loans from legal entities are subject to a daily rate of 0.0041% if the debtor is a company, while loans transactions granted to individuals are subject to IOF at a daily rate of 0.0082%. With regard to transactions with a pre-determined principal amount, the imposition of the daily rate is limited to 365 days, so the maximum IOF rate is 1.5% (if the debtor is a company) or 3% (if the debtor is an individual). Additionally, the IOF is imposed at an additional 0.38% rate with regard to all credit transactions.</p>
                  <p>Other specific rules apply for the imposition of the IOF on credit transactions where the principal amount is not determined and on insurance and securities transactions.</p>
                  <p>External credit transactions, in which the Brazilian party is the debtor, are not subject to the IOF imposed on credit transactions, but solely to the IOF imposed on foreign exchange transactions.</p>
                  <p>Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the IOF credit rates have been temporarily reduced to 0% for credit agreements concluded between 3 April 2020 and 31 December 2020.</p>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>Insurance transactions</title>
                  <p>IOF is levied on insurance transactions, including life insurance, labour accidents insurance and insurance on goods. The insured person is subject to IOF at different rates, varying from 0% to 25%, according to the type of insurance, on the premium.</p>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>Securities</title>
                  <p>IOF is levied on the acquisition, transfer, redemption, resettlement or payment for liquidation of securities at the maximum rate of 1.5% on the value of the transaction. A number of exemptions and zero-rate benefits is granted to listed security transactions.</p>
                  <p>Assignments of shares traded on the Brazilian stock exchange for the purpose of backing the issuance of depositary receipts traded abroad are subject to IOF at a 0% rate. Similarly, transactions involving financial derivatives are subject to IOF at a 0% rate.</p>
               </topic>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.3." label="9.6.3.">
               <taxtopics>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_12_1" score="3">Employer</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_13" score="3">Development Levies</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_51" score="3">Environmental / Green Taxes</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_5_64_4" score="3">Gas Flaring Taxes</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <taxtopics version="3.0">
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_12_1" score="3">Employer</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_13" score="3">Development Levies</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_51" score="3">Environmental / Green Taxes</taxtopic>
                  <taxtopic tc="1_10_64" score="3">Taxes on Oil &amp; Gas Activities</taxtopic>
               </taxtopics>
               <title>Contribution for intervention on the economic domain (CIDE)</title>
               <topic>
                  <title>CIDE technology</title>
                  <p>In the case of payment for services rendered by foreign service providers involving the supply of technology, technical assistance and specialized technical services, technical services and administrative assistance services (and similar services), trademark licensing, or licensing of patents, the Brazilian company (licensee) is subject to the CIDE (<emph type="i">Contribuição de Intervenção no Domínio Econômico</emph>) contribution at the rate of 10% on the total amount.</p>
                  <p>The CIDE contribution is due and payable by the Brazilian licensee. It is thus not withheld from the royalties or service fees to be paid to the non-resident. According to Binding Decision 158 (S<emph type="i">úmula</emph> 158), the withholding tax levied on outbound payments is included in the taxable base of CIDE contribution even if the paying source in Brazil bears the financial burden of the withholding tax.</p>
                  <p>The CIDE contribution is not imposed on cross-border payments for software licences, except for payments involving the acquisition of software rights (including transfer of technology/source code). In certain circumstances, the CIDE contribution rate is reduced to zero percent if the company paying the patent, trademark royalties or service fees benefits from certain tax incentives (e.g. tax incentives targeting certain technology activities – semiconductors, digital TV, etc.).</p>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>CIDE fuel</title>
                  <p>CIDE is also imposed on the import and commercialization of gasoline, diesel, kerosene, fuel oils, liquefied petroleum gas (including natural gas and naphtha derived) and ethanol (CIDE fuel).</p>
                  <p>The CIDE fuel is imposed per cubic metre of gasoline and diesel imported or sold. The CIDE fuel rates for kerosene, fuel oils, liquefied petroleum gas (including natural gas and naphtha derived) and ethanol, remain however at 0%.</p>
               </topic>
               <topic>
                  <title>CIDE-digital</title>
                  <p>The Chamber of Deputies is currently examining a proposed bill to create CIDE-digital to be levied on gross revenue derived by resident or non-resident companies from digital services targeting the Brazilian market. The proposal was submitted to the Chamber of Deputies as Bill 2,358/2020 on 4 May 2020.</p>
                  <p>Under the proposal, the CIDE-digital would be levied on gross revenue derived by resident or non-resident companies, provided that they belong to a group deriving in a calendar year with:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>annual global revenue exceeding BRL 3 billion; and</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>gross revenue exceeding BRL 100 million in the Brazilian market.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The CIDE-digital would be levied upon the receipt of revenue (i.e. the taxable event) from:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>the display of advertisements on a digital platform for users located in Brazil;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>making available digital platforms that allow users to contact and interact with each other for the purpose of selling goods or providing services directly between each other, provided that one of the users is located in Brazil; and</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>the transmission of data from users located in Brazil, which has been generated by such users or collected while they were using the digital platforms.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The CIDE-digital would be levied under the following progressive rates:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>1% on gross revenue up to BRL 150 million;</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>3% on gross revenue between BRL 150 million and BRL 300 million; and</p>
                     </item>
                     <item label="-">
                        <p>5% on gross revenue exceeding BRL 300 million.</p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </topic>
            </section>
            <section anchor="gtha_br_2020-11-01_s_9.6.4." label="9.6.4.">
               <title>Contribution on digital services</title>
               <p>A proposal to create a contribution on digital services (<emph type="i">Contribuição Social sobre Serviços Digitais</emph>, CSSD) is currently under discussion at the National Congress. The CSSD would be levied at a 3% rate on gross revenue derived by resident and non-resident companies (provided that they belong to a group deriving, in a calendar year, annual global revenue exceeding BRL 4.5 billion) from digital services targeting the Brazilian market.</p>
               <p>The CSSD would be levied upon the receipt of revenue (i.e. the taxable event) from:</p>
               <list>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the display of advertisements on a digital platform for users located in Brazil;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>making available digital platforms that allow users to contact and interact with each other for the purpose of selling goods or providing services directly between each other, provided that one of the users is located in Brazil; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item label="-">
                     <p>the transmission of data from users located in Brazil, which has been generated by such users or collected while they were using the digital platforms.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Users accessing digital platforms on devices physically located in Brazil will be considered users located in the country.</p>
            </section>
         </section>
      </section>
   </chapbody>
</country-chap>
